<kml xmlns="http://www.opengis.net/kml/2.2">
    <Placemark>
        <name>Adelaide Australia MF Radar</name>
        <description>type: MFRadar

            The Adelaide, Australia (34.56S, 138.48E; ~19 m alt) 1.98 MHz MF radar has been in operation since 1983 at
            the location of Buckingham Park, just outside of Adelaide. On day 359 of 2001 at 89 km altitude, the apex
            magnetic coordinates were (28.2,-149.8) degrees. The magnetic inclination and declination angles were 48.0
            deg and -6.4 deg. The magnetic local time at 0 Universal Time (UT) is about 0856 MLT. The solar local time
            (SLT) is UT plus 9 hours and 14 minutes (138.48/15.=9.232). Code 42 (LST-UT) was corrected from 1.E-03 hr to
            hhmm in Sep 2004.

            The original data files are hourly averages of the zonal and meridional velocity in Australian Central
            Standard Time (ACST), which is 9 hr 30 min later than UT. Samples are taken every 2 min, so a possible 30
            samples can be had between ACST 9:00:00 and ACST 9:59:00, which is labelled as hour 9:00:00 ACST. The
            midpoint is 9:30:00 ACST or 0:00:00 UT, or 9:14:00 SLT. Local times have been converted to the mid-point
            SLT, or 14 min (0.232 hr) are added to the begin LT.

            The MF operating frequency is 1.98 MHz, with a peak transmitter power of 25 kW, 50 kW starting in 1995. The
            radar operates as a spaced-antenna system (Vincent, 1986), relying on coherent echo signals from middle
            atmosphere ionization. The inter-pulse period is 12.5 and 25 millisec, respectively during the day and
            night. There are usually 32 coherent integrations during the day and 16 at night, using 256 samples in the
            full correlation analysis (FCA) of Briggs [1984] with built-in rejection criteria. [ie, want about 2 min or
            102.4 sec integration day or night, or 12.5x10-3sec * 32 integ * 256 samples = 102.4 sec and 25x10-3sec * 16
            integ * 256 samples = 102.4 sec.]

            The height coverage is 50-98 km during the day and 70-98 km during the night, at Adelaide. The pulse width
            is 30 microsec, giving a height resolution of 4.5 km assuming a simple rectangular wave pulse [range of
            heights illuminated by the wave pulse = velocity of light * pulse-width / 2 = 3x10**8 m/s * 30x10-6s / 2 =
            4.5 km]. However, the height range provided is every 2 km between 60 and 98 km.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-34.56,138.48,19.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>College Fabry-Perot</name>
        <description>type: FabryPerot

            The College, Alaska Fabry-Perot interferometer was located on the roof of the Geophysical Institute in the
            years reported here (1981-1983). This is at 64.7N and 148.1W in geographic coordinates, where the corrected
            geomagnetic coordinates are 64.9N and 100.3W. This is relatively close to the Chatanika incoherent scatter
            radar site at 65.1N and 147.4W, which operated between 1971 and 1982. The IGRF model gives a magnetic
            declination angle of about 25 degrees and inclination angle of 76 degrees for the measurement period.
            However, the measurements were made relative to the magnetic field direction where the declination was
            assumed to be 30 degrees. This is not significantly different from the true declination, so the derived
            horizontal results are reported as being in the magnetic directions. The measurements are all at 630.0 nm.
            All nights included are clear, or had cloudy periods removed.

            The zenith measurements are assumed to be on average zero throughout the night. All other measurements were
            taken in directions relative to the magnetic E, N, W and S directions at elevations angles between 20 and 45
            degrees, and were converted to horizontal directions assuming an emission layer centered at 225 km.

            The intensities are relative, (Code 2505) but are approximately within 25% of the true intensities in
            Rayleighs.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>64.7,-148.1</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>EISCAT: Tromso VHF Radar</name>
        <description>type: IncoherentScatterRadar

            The EISCAT (European Incoherent SCATter) facility in Scandinavia consists of a transimitter/receiver station
            at Tromso, Norway (69.6N, 19.2E), and receiver stations at Kiruna, Sweden (67.9N, 20.4E) and Sodankyla,
            Finland (67.4N, 26.6E). The facility has been in operation since 1981, and recently expanded to include a
            facility at Svalbard, which will have its own web page when data are included in the CEDAR Data Base.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>69.9,19.2</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Christchurch New Zealand MF Radar</name>
        <description>type: MFRadar

            The Christchurch MF radar (43.83 S, 172.68 E) in New Zealand is operated by the Physics Department of the
            University of Canterbury, Christchurch, New Zealand. It uses the partial-reflection, spaced antenna method
            (Fraser, 1984) and has contributed to mean wind and tidal studies (Fraser, 1968; Fraser 1989; Fraser et al
            1989; Manson et al., 1989, 1990, 1991). The mean solar local time (SLT) is about 11 hours and 31 minutes
            ahead of Universal Time (UT) (i.e., 172.68 E / 15 deg/hr = 11.51 hours = 11 hrs 31 min). The phases are in
            SLT.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-43.83,172.68</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Halley Antarctica HF Radar</name>
        <description>type: HFRadar

            The Halley HF radar is located in Antarctica (76 degs S, 26 deg W) and overlooks a section of ionosphere
            poleward of 78 deg that covers much of eastern Antarctica and includes South Pole station. The field
            -of-view is conjugate to the west coast of Greenland and the Goose Bay HF radar. It has operated since 1988.
            The facility is part of the SuperDARN network of HF radars that extends from western North America to
            Scandinavia in the Northern hemisphere and covers much of Antarctica in the Southern hemisphere. The
            SuperDARN radar for the most direct 2-D merging of Halley velocity data is located at Syowa, Antarctica.

            The radar forms and steers its beam by the phasing of transmissions from 16 elements in a linear antenna
            array. A second 4-element array provide the capability to measure elevation angle. The basic radar operation
            consists of the following steps: i) selection of a beam position (0-15) ii) search for the quietest 5-kHz
            channel about the assigned transmitting frequency (8-20 MHz) iii) repeated transmission of a multi-pulse
            sequence over the selected integration period and reception of backscattered signal with gating in range
            (1-70) iv) calculation of the auto-correlation functions (ACFs). These operations are usually carried out in
            sequence for the 16 beam positions, which collectively constitute 1 scan. The beam integration period is
            typically 6 or 7 sec, and the scan repeat time is 96 sec or 120 sec. Within a scan, beam 0 corresponds to
            the most westward beam position and beam 15 to the most eastward. The azimuth sector scanned is
            approximately 50 deg wide and is centered on 165 deg E of N.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-76.0,-26.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>SANAE Antarctica HF Radar</name>
        <description>type: HFRadar

            The SANAE (South African National Antarctic Expedition) HF radar is located in Antarctica (71.68 deg S,
            -2.85 deg E) and looks over a section of ionosphere poleward of 65 deg S that covers much of East
            Antarctica. It has operated since 1997. The facility is part of the SuperDARN network of HF radars that
            extends from Alaska to Scandinavia in the Northern hemisphere and covers much of Antarctica in the Southern
            hemisphere. The SuperDARN radar for the most direct 2-D merging of SANAE velocity data is located at Halley
            Station.

            The radar forms and steers its beam by the phasing of transmissions from 16 elements in a linear antenna
            array. It has no second array for deriving elevation angle information. The basic radar operation consists
            of the following steps: i) selection of a beam position (0-15) ii) search for the quietest 5-kHz channel
            about the assigned transmitting frequency (8-20 MHz) iii) repeated transmission of a multi-pulse sequence
            over the selected integration period and reception of backscattered signal with gating in range (1-70) iv)
            calculation of the auto-correlation functions (ACFs). These operations are usually carried out in sequence
            for the 16 beam positions, which collectively constitute 1 scan. The beam integration period is usually 7
            sec, and the scan repeat time is then 120 sec (2 min). Within a scan, beam 0 corresponds to the most
            westward beam position and beam 15 to the most eastward. The azimuth sector scanned is approximately 50 deg
            wide and is centered on 107.0 deg E of N.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-71.68,-2.85</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Poker Flat Alaska MF Radar</name>
        <description>type: MFRadar

            The Poker Flat, Alaska (65.126 N, 147.495 W; alt 208 m) 2.43 MHz MF radar has been in operation since 1998.
            On day 359 of 2001 at 89 km altitude, the apex magnetic coordinates were (65.4, -95.5) degrees. The magnetic
            inclination and declination angles were 77.4 deg and 24.1 deg. The magnetic local time at 0 Universal Time
            (UT) is about 1233 MLT. The solar local time (SLT) is UT minus 9 hours and 50 minutes (-147.495/15.=-9.833).

            The original data files are 30 min averages of the zonal, meridional and 'vertical' velocity in UT. The UT
            time is the midpoint UT, and is also listed as the midpoint SLT. Samples are taken every 3, 4 or 5 min, so 6
            to 10 samples can be had between UT 23:45:00 and UT 00:15:00. To improve data quality, 'median screening' is
            applied inside a 1-h bin. If data points lie outside a threshold standard deviation (code 4152) of usually
            1.5 inside a 1-hr bin, they are discarded. So the low qulity (jamped) data are rejected and then the
            remaining data are averaged over 30-min bins with a threshold of usually 30% (code 4151). The number of
            points used in each direction are in codes 422, 423 and 424.

            The 'vertical' velocities (code 1432, 'contaminated neutral vertical geographic wind (+up)') are from the
            beam in the vertical direction. The antenna array in a triangle has a different beam width for different
            azimuth direction, resulting in beam widths about 20-30 deg wide. Hence, the 'vertical' velocity will be
            contaminated by horizontal wind times the sine of 10 to 15 degrees (.17 to .26). Since the horizontal winds
            are stronger than the vertical winds, even the sign could be incorrect. The standard deviations of the
            'vertical' winds are also larger than the average values.

            The MF operating frequency is 1.95550 MHz, with a peak transmitter power of 50 kW. The radar operates as a
            spaced-antenna system (Vincent, 1986), relying on coherent echo signals from middle atmosphere ionization.
            The inter-pulse period is 12.5 millisec during the day and 25 millisec during the night. There are 80
            coherent integrations during the day and 40 at night, using 240 samples in the full correlation analysis
            (FCA) of Briggs [1984] with built-in rejection criteria. [ie, if want 240 sec or 4 min integration during
            day and night, then 12.5x10-3sec * 80 integ * 240 samples = 240 sec and 25x10-3sec * 40 integ * 240 samples
            = 240 sec.]

            Data sampling is done every 2 km usually between 60-98 km for Yamagawa (60-108 km for Wakkanai, 44-108 km
            for Poker Flat). The height range of wind velocity data is variable accoding to atmospheric and radio
            conditions and is usually about 70-90 km at Yamagawa and Wakkanai during the day and 80-90 km at night
            (60-90 km/70-90 km for Poker Flat for day/night conditions).

            The pulse width is 48 microsec (27 microsec before September 1996), giving a height resolution of approx.
            7.2 km (4.1 km) assuming a simple rectangular wave pulse. For the 48-microsec case, the range of heights
            illuminated by the wave pulse = velocity of light * pulse-width / 2 = 3x10**8 m/s * 48x10-6s / 2 = 7.2 km.
            However, neutral velocities are given every 2 km.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>65.126,-147.495,208.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Kauai, Hawaii MF RADAR</name>
        <description>type: MFRadar

            The Kauai, Hawaii (22.0N, 159.3W; 2 m alt) 1.98 MHz MF radar has been in operation since 1990. On day 359 of
            2001 at 89 km altitude, the apex magnetic coordinates were (22.6, -91.5) degrees. The magnetic inclination
            and declination angles were 38.6 deg and 10.1 deg. The magnetic local time at 0 Universal Time (UT) is about
            1249 MLT. The solar local time (SLT) is UT minus 10 hours and 37 minutes (-159.3/15.=-10.620).
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>22.0,-159.3,2.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Svalbard I.S. Radar</name>
        <description>type: IncoherentScatterRadar

            The EISCAT (European Incoherent SCATter) Svalbard Radar (ESR) consists of a transmitter and receiver in
            Longyearbyen, Norway (78.15N, 16.04E; 75.0 magnetic N). Observations were begun in 1996. The system was
            added to the EISCAT KST (Kiruna/Sodankyla/Tromso) tri-static facility in Scandinavia, which has its own web
            page.

            There are several common programs used for the World Days, which are a part of the CEDAR Database from the
            KST site, but not yet on a regular basis from the ESR site. There are many other experimental times which
            should be accessed with the aid of an EISCAT colleague.

            The power profiles are calibrated with an on-site ionosonde, and are then corrected for Te and Ti effects
            which are deduced from the auto-correlation functions (ACFs). The collision frequency model used is the CIRA
            1972 model atmosphere in Banks and Kockarts (1973), in Aeronmy Part A. The NO+ composition is assumed zero
            above 300 km.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>78.15,16.04</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>MU I.S. Radar, Shigaraki Japan</name>
        <description>type: IncoherentScatterRadar

            The Incoherent Scatter routine measurement with the MU (Middle and Upper atmosphere) radar (34.8N, 136.1E)
            uses 4 beam directions simultaneously, with the first 15 minutes of each hour devoted to single-pulse
            measurements (for electron density), and the last 45 minutes devoted to two-pulse (for ion drift velocity)
            or four-pulse (for ion/electron temperature) measurements. The radar operates at a frequency of 46.5 MHz and
            uses a beam width of 3.7 degrees. Measurements have been taken about 2 days per month starting on September
            17, 1986.

            The 4 beams are at an elevation angle of 70 degrees pointing towards magnetic north, east, south and west,
            assuming a declination angle of -5 degrees. The inclination angle is about 48 degrees, and the corrected
            magneitc latitude of the MU radar is about 25 degrees.

            The initial range resolution of the velocities is 38 km. Velocities are averaged between 220 and 455 km,
            where the altitude of the measurement is defined to be 338, the midpoint of the 235 km range. A running
            3-hour average of the ACF is computed as well as the height average before the line of sight (los) ion drift
            velocity is computed, so there are no error bars. The UT time is the midpoint of the 45 minutes of the
            middle hour.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>34.8,136.1</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Sondrestrom Fjord Michelson Interfer.</name>
        <description>type: MichelsonInterferometer

            A near infrared (NIR) BOMEM MB160 Michelson interferometer (MI) has operated at Sondrestrom Fjord (66.99 N,
            50.95 W), Greenland, 180 m above mean sea level since September, 1990.

            The MI scans the dark sky NIR airglow emissions between ~5000-10000 cm-1. A periscope directs the airglow
            into the MI sequentially from three locations at an elevation angle of 25 deg at azimuth angles of 0 (geog
            N), 120, and 240 deg. The periscope dwells at each position for about 15 min. Airglow hydroxyl Meinel (OH-M)
            band emissions peak at 87 km and are located between about 83 and 89 km. For an elevation angle of 25 deg,
            the 87 km peak is at a latitude spacing of 1.61 degrees, or about 179 km away.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>66.99,-50.95,180.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Arequipa, Peru Fabry-Perot</name>
        <description>type: FabryPerot

            The Fabry-Perot interferometer of the Arequipa Automatic Airglow Observatory (A3O) is operated jointly by
            the University of Pittsburgh and Clemson University under grants from the NSF Atmospheric Sciences Aeronomy
            division, with space and on-site technical support provided by the NASA Laser Satellite Tracking Station
            near Arequipa, Peru. The station is located at latitude 16.47 S and longitude 71.49 W at an elevation of
            2489 m. The apex magnetic latitude is about -12, with a magnetic dip latitude of about 3, an inclination
            angle of -6 to -7, and a declination between +1 and -2 between 1983 and 1999. The mean local solar time is
            behind UT by 4 hours and 46 minutes (-71.49/15 = -4.766 = -4h 46m). The FPI uses the atomic oxygen filter at
            630.0 nm, where the approximate emission height is assumed to be about 250 km.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-16.47,-71.49,2489.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>South Pole, Antarctica Michelson Inter.</name>
        <description>type: MichelsonInterferometer

            A near infrared (NIR) BOMEM MB160 Michelson interferometer (MI) has operated at South Pole Station (90.00S,
            2835 m) in Antarctica since January 1992.

            The MI scans the dark sky NIR airglow emissions between ~5000-10000 cm-1. A periscope directs the airglow
            into the MI sequentially from three locations at an elevation angle of 25 deg at azimuth angles of 0 (0 E),
            120 (120 E), and 240 (240 E) deg. The periscope dwells at each position for about 4-15 min. Airglow hydroxyl
            Meinel (OH-M) band emissions peak at 87 km and are located between about 83 and 89 km for an elevation angle
            of 25 deg, the 87 km peak is located at a latitude spacing of 1.6 degrees, or at 88.4 S.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-90.0,0.0,2835.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Kerguelen Is. HF radar</name>
        <description>type: HFRadar

            The Kerguelen Island HF radar is located in the southern Indian Ocean (49.35 deg S, 70.28 deg E; 58.9 mag S)
            and looks poleward. It has operated since 2000. The facility is part of the SuperDARN network of HF radars
            that extends from Alaska to Scandinavia in the Northern hemisphere and covers much of Antarctica in the
            Southern hemisphere. The SuperDARN radar for the most direct 2-D merging of SANAE velocity data is located
            at Syowa-East station.

            The radar forms and steers its beam by the phasing of transmissions from 16 elements in a linear antenna
            array. It has no second array for deriving elevation angle information. The basic radar operation consists
            of the following steps: i) selection of a beam position (0-15) ii) search for the quietest 5-kHz channel
            about the assigned transmitting frequency (8-20 MHz) iii) repeated transmission of a multi-pulse sequence
            over the selected integration period and reception of backscattered signal with gating in range (1-70) iv)
            calculation of the auto-correlation functions (ACFs). These operations are usually carried out in sequence
            for the 16 beam positions, which collectively constitute 1 scan. The beam integration period is usually 7
            sec, and the scan repeat time is then 120 sec (2 min). Within a scan, beam 0 corresponds to the most
            westward beam position and beam 15 to the most eastward. The azimuth sector scanned is approximately 50 deg
            wide and is centered on 107.0 deg E of N.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-49.35,70.28</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Wuppertal Germany OH Spectrometer</name>
        <description>type: Spectrometer

            The Wuppertal, Germany (51.3N, 7.2E) Czerny-Turner grating spectrometer scans in the near infrared between
            1.05 - 1.74 um with a spectral resolution of about 450. It has been operated by the University of Wuppertal
            since 1980. The instrument measures the nightglow hydroxyl [OH*]. The [OH*] emission layer is centered near
            87 km (+/-2 km) with a thickness of about 9 km.

            Measured parameters are the hydroxyl Meinel band rotational temperature (Code 812) in tenths of Kelvin. To
            reduce NLTE effects as much as possible, the (3,1) transition lines P1(2), P1(3) and P1(4) near 1.5 um are
            chosen for the measurements. More than 3100 average nightly mean temperatures are available continously from
            July 1980 until now with a gap in 1985/86. The instrument field-of-view in the zenith has a horizontal
            resolution of 20x20 km^2 (with respect to 86 km altitude). One spectrum is measured in 90 s.

            Rotational temperatures are derived from the relative intensities of the three lines. Hence, if there should
            be changes of spectrometer sensitivity, atmospheric transmission, or other factors the derived temperatures
            would not be affected unless such changes are wavelength dependent. Even in that case, influences would be
            small because the three line are close together (1.524 um, 1.533 um, 1.543 um).

            The relative error of nightly mean temperature values is estimated to be 1-2 K. This is derived from
            measurements during the whole night, and therefore, it still contains some atmospheric variability. Thus,
            the value must be considered as an upper limit for the relative error. The absolute temperature error is of
            the same magnitude. Spectral and absolute intensity calibrations are performed about once per year.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>51.3,7.2</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Yamagawa Japan MF radar</name>
        <description>type: MFRadar

            The Yamagawa, Japan (31.20N, 130.62E; alt ~70 m) 1.9550 MHz MF radar has been in operation since 1994. On
            day 359 of 2001 at 89 km altitude, the apex magnetic coordinates were (25.1,-157.3) degrees. The magnetic
            inclination and declination angles were 44.7 deg and -5.6 deg. The magnetic local time at 0 Universal Time
            (UT) is about 0826 MLT. The solar local time (SLT) is UT plus 8 hours and 42 minutes (130.62/15.=8.708).

            The original data files are 30 min averages of the zonal, meridional and 'vertical' velocity in UT. The UT
            time is the midpoint UT, and is also listed as the midpoint SLT. Samples are taken every 3, 4 or 5 min, so 6
            to 10 samples can be had between UT 23:45:00 and UT 00:15:00. To improve data quality, 'median screening' is
            applied inside a 1-h bin. If data points lie outside a threshold standard deviation (code 4152) of usually
            1.5 inside a 1-hr bin, they are discarded. So the low qulity (jamped) data are rejected and then the
            remaining data are averaged over 30-min bins with a threshold of usually 30% (code 4151). The number of
            points used in each direction are in codes 422, 423 and 424.

            The 'vertical' velocities (code 1432, 'contaminated neutral vertical geographic wind (+up)') are from the
            beam in the vertical direction. The antenna array in a triangle has a different beam width for different
            azimuth direction, resulting in beam widths about 20-30 deg wide. Hence, the 'vertical' velocity will be
            contaminated by horizontal wind times the sine of 10 to 15 degrees (.17 to .26). Since the horizontal winds
            are stronger than the vertical winds, even the sign could be incorrect. The standard deviations of the
            'vertical' winds are also larger than the average values.

            The MF operating frequency is 1.95550 MHz, with a peak transmitter power of 50 kW. The radar operates as a
            spaced-antenna system (Vincent, 1986), relying on coherent echo signals from middle atmosphere ionization.
            The inter-pulse period is 12.5 millisec during the day and 25 millisec during the night. There are 80
            coherent integrations during the day and 40 at night, using 240 samples in the full correlation analysis
            (FCA) of Briggs [1984] with built-in rejection criteria. [ie, if want 240 sec or 4 min integration during
            day and night, then 12.5x10-3sec * 80 integ * 240 samples = 240 sec and 25x10-3sec * 40 integ * 240 samples
            = 240 sec.]

            Data sampling is done every 2 km usually between 60-98 km for Yamagawa (60-108 km for Wakkanai, 44-108 km
            for Poker Flat). The height range of wind velocity data is variable accoding to atmospheric and radio
            conditions and is usually about 70-90 km at Yamagawa and Wakkanai during the day and 80-90 km at night
            (60-90 km/70-90 km for Poker Flat for day/night conditions).

            The pulse width is 48 microsec (27 microsec before September 1996), giving a height resolution of approx.
            7.2 km (4.1 km) assuming a simple rectangular wave pulse. For the 48-microsec case, the range of heights
            illuminated by the wave pulse = velocity of light * pulse-width / 2 = 3x10**8 m/s * 48x10-6s / 2 = 7.2 km.
            However, neutral velocities are given every 2 km.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>31.2,130.62,70.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Tirunveli India MF radar</name>
        <description>type: MFRadar

            The Tirunelveli, India (8.67N, 77.82E; 30 m alt) 1.98 MHz MF radar has been in continuous operation since
            December 1992. On day 359 of 2001 at 89 km altitude, the apex magnetic coordinates were (6.8, 149.8)
            degrees. The magnetic inclination and declination angles were 1.4 deg and -2.6 deg. The magnetic local time
            at 0 Universal Time (UT) is about 0554 MLT. The solar local time (SLT) is UT plus 5 hours and 11 minutes
            (77.82/15.=5.188).

            The original data files are hourly averages of the zonal and meridional velocity in Indian Standard Time
            (IST), which is 5 hours and 30 minutes later than UT. Samples are taken every 2 min, so a possible 30
            samples can be had between IST 0:00:00 and IST 0:59:00, which is labelled as hour 1:00:00 IST. These times
            have been converted to the mid-point solar local time (or 0:11 SLT or 0.188 SLT for this example).

            The MF radar system is identical to the one operating at Christmas island (2E,158W) and designed by Robert
            Vincent (robert.vincent@adelaide.edu.au) of the University of Adelaide in Australia (Vincent, 1991). The
            operating frequency is 1.98 MHz, with a peak transmitter power of 25 kW. The radar operates as a
            spaced-antenna system (Vincent, 1986), relying on coherent echo signals from middle atmosphere ionization.
            The inter-pulse period is 12.5 millisec during the day and 25 millisec during the night. There are 32
            coherent integrations during the day and 16 at night, using 256 samples in the full correlation analysis
            (FCA) of Briggs [1984] with built-in rejection criteria. [ie, want about 2 min or 102.4 sec integration
            during day and night, or 12.5x10-3sec * 32 integ * 256 samples = 102.4 sec and 25x10-3sec * 16 integ * 256
            samples = 102.4 sec.]

            The height coverage is 68-98 km during the day and 70-98 km during the night. The pulse width is 30
            microsec, giving a height resolution of 4.5 km assuming a simple rectangular wave pulse [range of heights
            illuminated by the wave pulse = velocity of light * pulse-width / 2 = 3x10**8 m/s * 30x10-6s / 2 = 4.5 km].
            However, neutral velocities are given every 2 km between 80 and 98 km since the ionization is less below 80
            km.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>8.67,77.82,30.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Stokkseyri (Iceland West) HF Radar</name>
        <description>type: HFRadar

            The Stokkseyri HF radar is located in western Iceland (63.86 deg N, -22.02 deg E) and looks to the west over
            a section of ionosphere that includes southern Greenland and northeastern Canada. It has operated since
            1994. The facility is part of the SuperDARN network of HF radars that extends from western North America to
            Scandinavia in the Northern hemisphere and covers much of Antarctica in the Southern hemisphere. The
            SuperDARN radar for the most direct 2-D merging of Stokkseyri velocity data is located at Goose Bay in
            Canada.

            The radar forms and steers its beam by the phasing of transmissions from 16 elements in a linear antenna
            array. A second 4-element array provides the capability to measure elevation angle. The basic radar
            operation consists of the following steps: i) selection of a beam position (0-15), ii) search for the
            quietest 5-kHz channel about the assigned transmitting frequency (8-20 MHz), iii) repeated transmission of a
            multi-pulse sequence over the selected integration period and reception of backscattered signal with gating
            in range (1-70), and iv) calculation of the auto-correlation functions (ACFs). These operations are usually
            carried out in sequence for the 16 beam positions, which collectively constitute 1 scan. The beam
            integration period is typically 6 or 7 sec, and the scan repeat time is 96 sec or 120 sec. Within a scan,
            beam 0 corresponds to the most westward beam position and beam 15 to the most eastward. The azimuth sector
            scanned is westward approximately 50 deg wide and is centered on -59 deg E of N.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>63.86,-22.02</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Hankasalmi Finland HF Radar</name>
        <description>type: HFRadar

            The Hankasalmi HF radar is located in southern Finland (62.32 deg N, 26.61 deg E) and looks to the west over
            a section of ionosphere that includes the Greenland sea and Svaalbard. It has operated since 1995. The
            facility is part of the SuperDARN network of HF radars that extends from western North America to
            Scandinavia in the Northern hemisphere and covers much of Antarctica in the Southern hemisphere. The
            SuperDARN radar for the most direct 2-D merging of Hankasalmi velocity data is located at Pykkvibaer,
            Iceland.

            The radar forms and steers its beam by the phasing of transmissions from 16 elements in a linear antenna
            array. A second 4-element array provides the capability to measure elevation angle. The basic radar
            operation consists of the following steps: i) selection of a beam position (0-15), ii) search for the
            quietest 5-kHz channel about the assigned transmitting frequency (8-20 MHz), iii) repeated transmission of a
            multi-pulse sequence over the selected integration period and reception of backscattered signal with gating
            in range (1-70), and iv) calculation of the auto-correlation functions (ACFs). These operations are usually
            carried out in sequence for the 16 beam positions, which collectively constitute 1 scan. The beam
            integration period is typically 6 or 7 sec, and the scan repeat time is 96 sec or 120 sec. Within a scan,
            beam 0 corresponds to the most westward beam position and beam 15 to the most eastward. The azimuth sector
            scanned is westward approximately 50 deg wide and is centered on -12 deg E of N.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>62.32,26.61</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Arrival Heights Fabry-Perot Interf Sp</name>
        <description>type: FabryPerot

            The Fabry-Perot Spectrometer at Arrival Heights, Antarctica (77.8296 S, 166.6627 E, 190.3 m ASL) has been
            operated since 2002 by the Department of Earth and Space Sciences, University of Washington. The apex
            magnetic coordinates of Arrival Heights at 250 km height in 2002 were (-80.1, -34.3) with a magnetic
            declination of 142.6 deg, an inclination of -81.3 deg, and 0 UT at 17.15 MLT.

            The dispersing element of the spectrometer is an air-spaced, 14 cm diameter effective clear-aperture
            Fabry-Perot etalon, which is both self-aligning and self-stabilizing. It is operated near the optimum
            operational point (2.0 cm spacer) for kinetic temperature determinations (Hernandez, 1988).

            The spectrometer operates simultaneously at two wavelengths, which are arbitrarily selected by the use of
            dichroic mirrors and narrow (0.3 nm wide) interference filters. The inherent stability of the spectrometer
            is about 0.5 m/s (632.8 nm) for periods of months, because of its self-stabilizing properties. The
            instrumental internal stability calibration is updated every 9 s.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-77.8296,166.6627,190.3</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Arecibo P.R. Fabry-Perot</name>
        <description>type: FabryPerot

            The Arecibo Observatory Fabry-Perot interferometer (18.35N, 66.75W) has been in operation since 1972. The
            data reported here (1980-1988), are atomic oxygen measurements at 630.0 nm. According to the IGRF model, the
            magnetic declination angle at Arecibo varied between -9.4 and -10.4 degrees between February 1980 and July
            1988, while the inclination angle varied between 48.8 and 47.9 degrees. All nights are clear, or had cloudy
            periods removed. The approximate emission height is assumed to be 300 km. Scans in azimuth were done at a 30
            degree elevation height, with usually one zenith measurment per scan.

            The intensities are relative, (Code 2505) but are approximately correct to within a factor of two of the
            true emission intensities in Rayleighs. The Doppler half-width is related to the square root of the neutral
            temperature assuming a Gaussian emission shape. The instrument was not optimized to measure Doppler widths,
            but was broadened to increase the signal throughput in order to make better measurements of the Doppler
            shift, which is related to the neutral velocity. Because of uncertainties in the half-width, the conversion
            to temperature was not made.

            In some of the data files the zenith observations were used as a zero reference in the analysis (Code
            4050=1), while for others, all of the measurements for a given night were used (Code 4050=0) by assuming
            that each component of the horizontal neutral wind velocity can be represented by a second order Taylor
            expansion (constant horizontal velocity gradients) about a point directly above the station. A harmonic
            analysis gives the zonal (Ue) and meridional (Un) velocities, and two parameters related to the deformation
            of the flow, d(Ue)/dx and d(Un)/dy, where x and y are the eastward and northward directions, respectively.
            The vertical wind velocity (Uz) is thus not measured directly, but is derived from the DC term of the
            expansion. Values of Uz are inferred as the product of the horizontal divergence of the horizontal wind
            velocity, Uh, and the neutral scale height H: i.e., Uz = H del(Uh) where H = 50 km.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>18.35,-66.75</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Daytona Beach FL, USA Michelson Inter.</name>
        <description>type: MichelsonInterferometer

            A near infrared (NIR) BOMEM DA-8 Michelson interferometer (MI) has operated at Daytona Beach (29.19 N, 81.05
            W), Florida, USA, 0 m above mean sea level since September, 1996.

            The MI scans the dark sky NIR airglow emissions between ~5000-10000 cm-1. A periscope directs the airglow
            into the MI sequentially from three locations at an elevation angle of 25 deg at azimuth angles of 0 (geog
            N), 120, and 240 deg. The periscope dwells at each position for about 5 min. Airglow hydroxyl Meinel (OH-M)
            band emissions peak at 87 km and are located between about 83 and 89 km. For an elevation angle of 25 deg,
            the 87 km peak is at a latitude spacing of 1.61 degrees, or about 179 km away.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>29.19,-81.05,0.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Platteville Colorado ST (MEDAC) Radar</name>
        <description>type: MeteorWindRadar

            The Platteville, CO ST (MEDAC) radar is located at (40 N, 105 W). The MEDAC (Meteor Echo Detection And
            Collection) sytem added to the ST (STratospheric) radar makes observations of winds measured from the
            backscatter off meteor trails. The system is described in Avery et al. (1990). The original observations are
            described in local time, which is 7 hours later than UT. (Mountain Standard Time = UT - 7 hours.) The mean
            solar local time (SLT) is about 7 hours after UT. (i.e., -105 E/15 deg/hr = -7.00 hours). Therefore, no
            adjustment was made to the phase, since the local time is very close to the solar local time.

            These are the analyzed data on the neutral winds in the mesosphere and lower thermosphere during or
            including the LTCS-2 period, 5-10 December 1988. This condensed format is consistent with the analyzed data
            from other sites as well, and is prepared in order to facilitate research work. However, users need to
            inform the data suppliers that they are using the data in case of updates or changes, and to insure that the
            data are being used and interpreted properly.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>40.0,-105.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Mount John New Zealand Fabry-Perot</name>
        <description>type: FabryPerot

            The Fabry-Perot Interferometric Spectrometer at Mount John Observatory, New Zealand (43.98S, 170.42E) has
            been operated since 1991 by the Graduate Program in Geophysics, University of Washington, in cooperation
            with the Physics and Astronomy Department of the University of Canterbury, NZ, and the Geophysical Institute
            of the University of Alaska.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-43.98,170.42</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Resolute Bay Fabry-Perot Interf Sp</name>
        <description>type: FabryPerot

            The Fabry-Perot Interferometer at Resolute Bay, Canada (74.73N, -94.89E, 87 m ASL) has been operated since
            2003 by the High Altitude Observatory of the National Center For Atmospheric Research. The apex magnetic
            coordinates of Resolute Bay at 250 km height in 2004 were (83.1, -39.0) with a magnetic declination of -24.4
            deg, an inclination of 88.0 deg, and 0 UT at 16.31 MLT.

            The dispersing element of the interferometer is an air-spaced, 10 cm diameter effective clear-aperture
            Fabry-Perot etalon. It has a fixed gap of 2.0 cm. The etalon is housed in a temperature controlled chamber
            (Wu et al. 2004). The instrument detector is a back illuminated CCD camera with 1024x1024 pixels and 1x1
            inch size. The CCD temperature is set at -55 C. The readout noise of the CCD is 4 electrons.

            The interferometer has an 8-position filter wheel. The wavelengths used at Resolute Bay are:

            1. The red line (630.0 nm, kindat=17001) of atomic oxygen (OI) with a typical emission height peak in the
            range 210 to 300 km.
            2. The green line (557.7 nm, kindat=17002) of atomic oxygen (OI), with a typical emission height peak range
            near 94-98 km.
            3. The [OH] line (892.0 nm, kindat=17003) of the nightglow excited hydroxyl [OH*] with an emission peak
            between about 87 and 91 km.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>74.73,-94.89,87.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Syowa East (Antarctica) HF Radar</name>
        <description>type: HFRadar

            The Syowa East HF radar is located in Antarctica (69.00 deg S, 39.58 deg E) and looks over a section of
            ionosphere poleward of 70 deg S that includes the east Antarctica ice cap and the southern ocean. It has
            operated since 1997. The facility is part of the SuperDARN network of HF radars that extends from Alaska to
            Scandinavia in the Northern hemisphere and covers much of Antarctica in the Southern hemisphere. The
            SuperDARN radar for the most direct 2-D merging of Syowa velocity data is located at Kerguelen.

            The radar forms and steers its beam by the phasing of transmissions from 16 elements in a linear antenna
            array. A second 4-element array provide the capability to measure elevation angle. The basic radar operation
            consists of the following steps: i) selection of a beam position (0-15) ii) search for the quietest 5-kHz
            channel about the assigned transmitting frequency (8-20 MHz) iii) repeated transmission of a multi-pulse
            sequence over the selected integration period and reception of backscattered signal with gating in range
            (1-70) iv) calculation of the auto-correlation functions (ACFs). These operations are usually carried out in
            sequence for the 16 beam positions, which collectively constitute 1 scan. The beam integration period is
            usually 7 sec, and the scan repeat time is then 120 sec (2 min). Within a scan, beam 0 corresponds to the
            most westward beam position and beam 15 to the most eastward. The azimuth sector scanned is approximately 50
            deg wide and is centered on 107.0 deg E of N, or about 52 degrees east of the look direction for Syowa
            South.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-69.0,39.58</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Millstone Hill I.S. Radar</name>
        <description>type: IncoherentScatterRadar

            The incoherent scatter transmitter station at Millstone Hill, Massachusetts (42.6N, 71.5W) has been in
            operation since 1960. The facility is part of and operated by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.

            ISR data comes from the fixed zenith antenna, the steerable antenna, or both.

            The electron densities from the power profile were calibrated with an on-site ionosonde, where recently,
            this ionosonde has been the University of Massachusetts at Lowell digisonde. Since the Coast Guard uses some
            of the frequencies needed to properly scan the ionosphere, calibration can sometimes be difficult. The
            calibrated electron density is then corrected for Te and Ti effects, where Te and Ti come from
            auto-correlation fits. The calibration and auto-correlation fits now have the same height resolution,
            although in the past, the auto-correlation fits had lower height resolution.

            The ion composition changes from mostly O2+ and NO+ at lower altitudes, to mostly O+, and then to H+ and
            some He+ at higher altitudes. Above 400 km, the percent H+ is computed along with the major ion O+. At lower
            altitudes, the ratio of molecular ions to the total number of ions is modeled as specified by the FORTRAN
            code segment below.

            REAL FUNCTION PMF(Z)
            Z1=AMIN1(-(Z-120.)/40.,50.)
            H=10.-6.*EXP(Z1)
            Z2=AMIN1(-(Z-180.)/H, 50.)
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>42.6,-71.5</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Poker Flat 4 Channel Photometer</name>
        <description>type: MultiChannelPhotometer

            The Aerospace 4 channel filter photometer at Poker Flat, Alaska (65.12N, 212.57E) was developed to estimate
            the energy flux of auroral electrons, their average energy Eo (usually from 0.1 to 30 keV using a modified
            Gaussian or Maxwellian shape), and a scale factor fo for the atomic oxygen densities [O] from an MSIS model
            atmosphere. The [O] densities using the scaling factor fo can be compared to GUVI/TIMED estimates. The
            technique is only valid for clear night conditions where the solar zenith angle (sza) is greater than 102
            deg (code 4102=1), and there is enough auroral emission (427.8 nm brightness, code 2421). Poker Flat apex
            magnetic coordinates are (65.44, -95.56) at 110 km in 2001, with 0 UT corresponding to 12.93 MLT. The
            magnetic inclination and declination angles are 77.41 deg and 24.89 deg. The photometer looks up the
            magnetic field line with a field of view (fov) of about 1 deg. The data rate can be programmed, but
            typically each channel is integrated for 1 sec, where the whole cycle including filter moves takes about 8
            sec.

            The 4 channels correspond to:

            1. N2+ (427.8 nm, blue) first negative group (1NG) 0,1 molecular band
            2. OI (630.0 nm, red) forbidden
            3. OI (844.6 nm, eight) permitted
            4. N2 (871.0 nm or 871.4 nm) first positive group (1PG) 2,1 molecular band
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>56.12,-147.43</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Peach Mountain Fabry-Perot</name>
        <description>type: FabryPerot

            The Peach Mountain (also known as Stinchfield Woods) Fabry-Perot interferometer, operated by the Space
            Physics Research Laboratory, Department of Atmospheric, Oceanic and Space Sciences of the University of
            Michigan is located at latitude 42.40N and longitude 86.93W, and at an altitude of 955 ft.

            Currently, the interferometer observes the line profile of the forbidden emission OI (5577 A) and OH (8920
            A). The geophysical parameters obtained from the data reduction are the gas kinetic temperature of the
            emitting region from the natural width of the sky profile, the line of sight wind from the Doppler shift of
            the sky profile, and the surface brightness of the emission line. OI (5577 A) nightglow emission is
            generally believed to issue from the altitude range 85 to 300 km, with the major contribution originating
            from a narrow height interval roughly 10 to 15 km broad centered at 97 km. Similarly, the Meinel OH emission
            also issues from a broad altitudinal range though centered at a lower altitude. Thus, it is difficult to
            assign a unique altitude to each ground based OI (5577 A) and OH (8920 A) interferometer measurement. If no
            other information is available, we generally ascribe 97 km as the altitude of OI (5577 A) emission and 86 km
            for the OH emission.

            Line of sight winds derived from the observed shift of the emission line from a zero reference position
            requires the determination of a zero wind. The reference zero wind is taken to be the average of an entire
            nights vertical wind data. Generally, the four cardinal directions are also sampled as well as the vertical.
            There is no exclusion of any data in the CEDAR Data Base, so cloudy night fits are also included. The cloud
            cover (code 440) measured by the Detroit Metro airport meteorological station is given in octas of the sky
            covered. Values range from 0 (clear) to 9 (overcast). In the summary plots, wind measurements were not
            plotted unless the cloud cover was 0-3. Temperatures and relative emission measurements were not plotted
            unless the cloud cover was 0-6.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>42.4,-86.93,291.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Obninsk Russia Meteor Wind Radar</name>
        <description>type: MeteorWindRadar

            The Obninsk, Russia (55.11N, 36.51E; ~172 m above msl) 33.3 MHz meteor radar has been in operation since
            1964. On day 359 of 2001 at 89 km altitude, the apex magnetic coordinates were (51.2, 111.0) degrees. The
            magnetic inclination and declination angles were 70.5 deg and 8.3 deg. The magnetic local time at 0
            Universal Time (UT) is about 0219 MLT. The solar local time (SLT) is UT plus 2 hours and 26 minutes
            (36.51/15=2.434). With no height ranging, the observations come approximately from 95 km.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>55.11,36.51,172.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Millstone Hill: zenith UHF antenna</name>
        <description>type: IncoherentScatterRadar

            The incoherent scatter transmitter station at Millstone Hill, Massachusetts (42.6N, 71.5W) has been in
            operation since 1960. The facility is part of and operated by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.

            ISR data comes from the fixed zenith antenna, the steerable antenna, or both.

            The electron densities from the power profile were calibrated with an on-site ionosonde, where recently,
            this ionosonde has been the University of Massachusetts at Lowell digisonde. Since the Coast Guard uses some
            of the frequencies needed to properly scan the ionosphere, calibration can sometimes be difficult. The
            calibrated electron density is then corrected for Te and Ti effects, where Te and Ti come from
            auto-correlation fits. The calibration and auto-correlation fits now have the same height resolution,
            although in the past, the auto-correlation fits had lower height resolution.

            The ion composition changes from mostly O2+ and NO+ at lower altitudes, to mostly O+, and then to H+ and
            some He+ at higher altitudes. Above 400 km, the percent H+ is computed along with the major ion O+. At lower
            altitudes, the ratio of molecular ions to the total number of ions is modeled as specified by the FORTRAN
            code segment below.

            REAL FUNCTION PMF(Z)
            Z1=AMIN1(-(Z-120.)/40.,50.)
            H=10.-6.*EXP(Z1)
            Z2=AMIN1(-(Z-180.)/H, 50.)
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>42.6,-71.5</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Davis, Antarctica MF radar</name>
        <description>type: MFRadar

            The Davis, Antarctica (68.60S, 77.97E; ~1 m alt) 1.94 MHz MF radar has been in operation since April 1994.
            On day 359 of 2001 at 89 km altitude, the apex magnetic coordinates were (64.1, 152.4) degrees. The magnetic
            inclination and declination angles were 81.7 deg and 21.7 deg. The magnetic local time at 0 Universal Time
            (UT) is about 0505 MLT. The solar local time (SLT) is UT plus 5 hours and 12 minutes (77.97/15.=5.198). Code
            42 (LST-UT) was corrected from 1.E-03 hr to hhmm in Sep 2004.

            The original data files are hourly averages of the zonal and meridional velocity in Local Time (LT), which
            is 5 hours later than UT. Smaples are taken every 2 min, so a possible 30 samples can be had between
            05:00:00 LT and 06:00:00 LT. The midpoint is 05:30:00 LT or 0:30:00 UT, or 5:42:00 SLT. Local times have
            been converted to the mid-point SLT, or 42 min (0.618 hr) are added to the beginning LT hour.

            The MF operating frequency is 1.94 MHz, with a peak transmitter power of 25 kW, 40 kW starting in 2004. The
            radar operates as a spaced-antenna system (Vincent, 1986), relying on coherent echo signals from middle
            atmosphere ionization. The inter-pulse period is 12.5 and 25 millisec, respectively during the day and
            night. There are usually 32 coherent integrations during the day and 16 at night, using 256 samples in the
            full correlation analysis (FCA) of Briggs [1984] with built-in rejection criteria. [ie, want about 2 min or
            102.4 sec integration day or night, or 12.5x10-3sec * 32 integ * 256 samples = 102.4 sec and 25x10-3sec * 16
            integ * 256 samples = 102.4 sec.]

            The height coverage is 50-100 km during the day or night at Davis. The pulse width is 30 microsec, giving a
            height resolution of 4.5 km assuming a simple rectangular wave pulse [range of heights illuminated by the
            wave pulse = velocity of light * pulse-width / 2 = 3x10**8 m/s * 30x10-6s / 2 = 4.5 km]. However, the height
            range provided is every 2 km between 50 and 100 km starting in 2003, and 50 and 98 km earlier.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-68.6,77.97,1.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Resolute Bay, Canada Michelson Interf.</name>
        <description>type: MichelsonInterferometer

            A near infrared (NIR) BOMEM MB160 Michelson interferometer (MI) has operated at Resolute Bay (74.68 N, 94.90
            W), 1 m above mean sea level in Canada since September, 1996.

            The MI scans the dark sky NIR airglow emissions between ~5000-10000 cm-1. The airglow is observed at an
            elevation angle of 25 deg towards the north (0 deg azimuth) and is averaged over about 6 min. Airglow
            hydroxyl Meinel (OH-M) band emissions peak at 87 km and are located between about 83 and 89 km. For an
            elevation angle of 25 deg, the 87 km peak is located at a latitude spacing of 1.61 degrees, or at 76.29 N,
            or 179 km away.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>74.68,-94.9,1.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>EISCAT: Tromso antenna</name>
        <description>type: IncoherentScatterRadar

            The EISCAT (European Incoherent SCATter) facility in Scandinavia consists of a transimitter/receiver station
            at Tromso, Norway (69.6N, 19.2E), and receiver stations at Kiruna, Sweden (67.9N, 20.4E) and Sodankyla,
            Finland (67.4N, 26.6E). The facility has been in operation since 1981, and recently expanded to include a
            facility at Svalbard, which will have its own web page when data are included in the CEDAR Data Base.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>69.9,19.2</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Kapuskasing HF Radar</name>
        <description>type: HFRadar

            The Kapuskasing HF radar is located in northern Ontario (49.39 deg N, -82.32 deg E) and looks over a section
            of ionosphere poleward of 50 deg N that covers north-central Canada including Hudson Bay and the Canadian
            arctic archipelago. It has operated since 1993. The facility is part of the SuperDARN network of HF radars
            that extends from western North America to Scandinavia in the Northern hemisphere and covers much of
            Antarctica in the Southern hemisphere. The SuperDARN radar for the most direct 2-D merging of Kapuskasing
            velocity data is located at Saskatoon, Saskatchewan.

            The radar forms and steers its beam by the phasing of transmissions from 16 elements in a linear antenna
            array. A second 4-element array provides the capability to measure elevation angle. The basic radar
            operation consists of the following steps: i) selection of a beam position (0-15), ii) search for the
            quietest 5-kHz channel about the assigned transmitting frequency (8-20 MHz), iii) repeated transmission of a
            multi-pulse sequence over the selected integration period and reception of backscattered signal with gating
            in range (1-70), and iv) calculation of the auto-correlation functions (ACFs). These operations are usually
            carried out in sequence for the 16 beam positions, which collectively constitute 1 scan. The beam
            integration period is typically 6 or 7 sec, and the scan repeat time is 96 sec or 120 sec. Within a scan,
            beam 0 corresponds to the most westward beam position and beam 15 to the most eastward. The azimuth sector
            scanned is westward approximately 50 deg wide and is centered on -12 deg E of N.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>49.39,-82.32</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Durham N Hampshire Meteor Wind Radar</name>
        <description>type: MeteorWindRadar

            These are monthly climatology neutral tidal winds in the mesosphere and lower thermosphere for data taken
            between 1978 and 1982 by the meteor wind radar at Durham, New Hampshire.

            The meteor wind radar at Durham, New Hampshire (43.12 Deg.N, 70.94 Deg.W) has operated routinely during most
            years since 1974. The radar looks at 45 deg. elevation in the Northeast and Northwest directions with
            beamwidths of +-20 degrees. The system is a computer controlled coherent pulsed radar at 36.8 Mhz.
            Measurements are made of the direction cosines, slant range, and slant range doppler. Since a horizontal
            wind is assumed, only measurements with zenith angles less than 60 degrees are used in the tidal analysis.
            The height of the meteor trail reflection points have a Gaussian distribution centered at approximately 95
            km with a standard deviation of approximately 9 km.

            Significant results are achieved by averaging over 4 days. These are the 12 monthly climatologies created by
            binning 4-day averages over 5 years in the appropriate month. The tidal analysis is based on the method
            developed by Groves (1959) using 30 coefficients. The results are least mean square fits to the data. The
            error bars are about 8 m/s at 80 and 107 km, and are about 5 m/s at 95 km. The phases are given only to the
            nearest hour, which refers to Eastern Standard Time (EST = UT - 5 hrs). The local mean solar time for Durham
            is the Universal Time minus 4 hours and 44 minutes.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>43.12,-70.94</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Millstone Hill: steerable UHF antenna</name>
        <description>type: IncoherentScatterRadar

            The incoherent scatter transmitter station at Millstone Hill, Massachusetts (42.6N, 71.5W) has been in
            operation since 1960. The facility is part of and operated by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.

            ISR data comes from the fixed zenith antenna, the steerable antenna, or both.

            The electron densities from the power profile were calibrated with an on-site ionosonde, where recently,
            this ionosonde has been the University of Massachusetts at Lowell digisonde. Since the Coast Guard uses some
            of the frequencies needed to properly scan the ionosphere, calibration can sometimes be difficult. The
            calibrated electron density is then corrected for Te and Ti effects, where Te and Ti come from
            auto-correlation fits. The calibration and auto-correlation fits now have the same height resolution,
            although in the past, the auto-correlation fits had lower height resolution.

            The ion composition changes from mostly O2+ and NO+ at lower altitudes, to mostly O+, and then to H+ and
            some He+ at higher altitudes. Above 400 km, the percent H+ is computed along with the major ion O+. At lower
            altitudes, the ratio of molecular ions to the total number of ions is modeled as specified by the FORTRAN
            code segment below.

            REAL FUNCTION PMF(Z)
            Z1=AMIN1(-(Z-120.)/40.,50.)
            H=10.-6.*EXP(Z1)
            Z2=AMIN1(-(Z-180.)/H, 50.)
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>42.6,-71.5</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Polar Cap Geomagnetic Index: Vostok</name>
        <description>type: Magnetometer

            The Vostok ground magnetometer station is located in Antarctica (-78.463 S, 106.826 E) and has been operated
            by the Arctic and Antarctic Research Institute of St. Petersburg since 1958. The analog data have been
            digitized for 1978 and 1979, and for 1983-1995. A 1-sec digital magnetometer was installed in 1996. The
            station is part of the former Soviet Union's scientific exploration of Antarctica, which started in 1957
            during the International Geophysical Year (IGY). It is located near the center of the Antarctic ice sheet,
            about 3488 m above mean sea level, and about 1250 km from McMurdo and about 1500 km from Mirny on the coast.

            Vostok is located in the polar cap at a high magnetic latitude. In 1978, the magnetic field at the surface
            was about 60950 nT, with an inclination angle of -77.682 degrees, a declination angle of -11.835 degrees,
            and an apex magnetic location of (-83.30, 53.56). In 2001, the magnetic field at the surface was about 59470
            nT, with an inclination angle of -76.807 degrees, a declination angle of -12.019 degrees, and an apex
            magnetic location of (-83.31, 55.11). The apex magetic location of -83.3 is very close to the corrected
            geomagnetic (cgm) location of -83.4 cgmlat used for Vostok.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-78.463,106.826</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Saint Santin: Montpazier receiver</name>
        <description>type: IncoherentScatterRadar

            The incoherent scatter transmitter station at St. Santin, France (44.6N, 2.2E) operated between 1963 and
            1987. The CEDAR Data Base holds all the data taken from 1966 until the end. Up until June 1973 and after
            July of 1986, the only receiver station operating was located at Nancay (47.4N, 2.2E). Between 1973 and
            1986, 2 other receivers also operated at Montpazier (44.7N, 0.8E) and at Mende (44.5N, 3.45E).

            In general, the daytime height range is 105 to 350 km, while the nighttime height range is 200 to 500 km.
            Before January 1, 1969, the faraday correction is not taken into account in the computation. The spectrum
            are analysed following the scheme described in Waldteufel (1970). The ion drift component is quasi parallel
            to the magnetic field as measured by the Nancay receiving station. Because the transmitter is not located at
            the receiving location, the bisector velocity is plotted for the period when only Nancay data were received.
            When all 3 receivers were on, then the data are 30 minute averages and the ion drifts in the geomagnetic
            coordinate system are calculated.

            There are 4 areas in the summary plots. There are image plots as a function of height and time of the
            electron density, electron temperature, and ion temperature. Bin sizes are 40 minutes in time and 40 km in
            height. For the Nancay period alone there is also an image plot of the bisector velocity, while this is
            replaced by line plots of the ion drift in the perpendicular east, north and parallel directions at the
            altitude closest to 300 km. when there are 3 receivers.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>44.6,2.2</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Watson Lake, Canada Fabry-Perot</name>
        <description>type: FabryPerot

            The Watson Lake Fabry-Perot interferometer, operated by the Space Physics Research Laboratory, Department of
            Atmospheric, Oceanic and Space Sciences of the University of Michigan is located at latitude 60.055N and
            longitude 128.58W, and at an altitude of 2950 feet. The FPI operated from 11/91-4/92 and 11/92-5/93.

            Currently, the interferometer observes the line profile of the forbidden emission OI (6300 A). The
            geophysical parameters obtained from the data reduction are the gas kinetic temperature of the emitting
            region from the natural width of the sky profile, the line of sight wind from the Doppler shift of the sky
            profile, and the surface brightness of the emission line. OI (6300 A) nightglow emission is generally
            believed to issue from the altitude range 175 to 500 km, with the major contribution originating from a
            narrow height interval (a few scale heights thick) centered roughly one neutral scale height below the
            altitude of maximum electron density. Thus, the peak altitude of emission and the parameters of the F region
            are interdependent and it is difficult to assign a unique altitude to each ground based OI (6300 A)
            interferometer measurement. If no other information is available, we generally ascribe 250 km as the
            altitude of emission.

            Line of sight winds derived from the observed shift of the emission line from a zero reference position
            requires the determination of a zero wind. The reference zero wind is taken to be the average of an entire
            nights vertical wind data. Generally, the four cardinal directions are also sampled as well as the vertical.
            There is no exclusion of any data in the CEDAR Data Base, so cloudy night fits are also included. The cloud
            cover (code 440) measured by the Watson Lake meteorological station is given in octas of the sky covered.
            Values range from 0 (clear) to 9 (overcast).

            Summary plots of the relative emission, neutral temeprature and vertical wind are plotted with error bars
            for the vertical look direction. For look directions in opposite cardinal directions, horizontal winds are
            plotted without error bars. For periods where there are plots of the vertical wind, but not of the
            horizontal wind, then the look directions are not cardinal. In the summary plots, wind measurements were not
            plotted unless the cloud cover was 0-3. Temperatures and relative emission measurements were not plotted
            unless the cloud cover was 0-6. For the period of data in the CEDAR Data Base, the cloud cover was 0-3 38%
            of the time, and 0-6 48% of the time.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>60.055,-128.58,899.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Saskatoon Canada MF Radar</name>
        <description>type: MFRadar

            The Saskatoon MF radar is located in the province of Saskatchewan in Canada (52N, 107W). The solar local
            time (SLT) is Universal Time (UT) minus 7 hours and 10 minutes. (SLT = UT - 7:10). The phases are in SLT and
            the measurement days start at 0 UT. The Saskatoon MF radar has provided considerable mean winds (Manson et
            al., 1990a and 1991a) and tidal data (Manson et al, 1989) since 1979. LTCS-1 and LTCS-2 are described for
            all middle atmosphere radars in Manson et al (1990b,1991b). MF radars use the "spaced antenna" method.
            Harmonic analysis is applied to hourly mean winds (weighted by data yield per hour) at individual heights to
            obtain tides for the prime LTCS or stated intervals. Typical standard deviations for means, 12-hour and
            24-hour tides are in the above LTCS papers. Tides of the month for Saskatoon are means of 4-day fits (the
            amplitudes are arithmetic means). Data up to 99 km are real heights --- above, they are from the E-region, a
            layer about 5 km centered near 102 km.

            These are the analyzed data on the neutral winds in the mesosphere and lower thermosphere during or
            including the LTCS-1 period, 21-25 September 1987. This condensed format is consistent with the analyzed
            data from other sites as well, and is prepared in order to facilitate research work. However, users need to
            inform the data suppliers that they are using the data in case of updates or changes, and to insure that the
            data are being used and interpreted properly.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>52.0,-107.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Saint Santin: Nancay receiver</name>
        <description>type: IncoherentScatterRadar

            The incoherent scatter transmitter station at St. Santin, France (44.6N, 2.2E) operated between 1963 and
            1987. The CEDAR Data Base holds all the data taken from 1966 until the end. Up until June 1973 and after
            July of 1986, the only receiver station operating was located at Nancay (47.4N, 2.2E). Between 1973 and
            1986, 2 other receivers also operated at Montpazier (44.7N, 0.8E) and at Mende (44.5N, 3.45E).

            In general, the daytime height range is 105 to 350 km, while the nighttime height range is 200 to 500 km.
            Before January 1, 1969, the faraday correction is not taken into account in the computation. The spectrum
            are analysed following the scheme described in Waldteufel (1970). The ion drift component is quasi parallel
            to the magnetic field as measured by the Nancay receiving station. Because the transmitter is not located at
            the receiving location, the bisector velocity is plotted for the period when only Nancay data were received.
            When all 3 receivers were on, then the data are 30 minute averages and the ion drifts in the geomagnetic
            coordinate system are calculated.

            There are 4 areas in the summary plots. There are image plots as a function of height and time of the
            electron density, electron temperature, and ion temperature. Bin sizes are 40 minutes in time and 40 km in
            height. For the Nancay period alone there is also an image plot of the bisector velocity, while this is
            replaced by line plots of the ion drift in the perpendicular east, north and parallel directions at the
            altitude closest to 300 km. when there are 3 receivers.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>44.6,2.2</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Inuvik NWT Fabry-Perot Interferometer</name>
        <description>type: FabryPerot

            The fixed-gap imaging Fabry-Perot Spectrometer (FPS) or Interferometer (FPI) at Inuvik in the North West
            Territories (NWT) of Canada (68.33N, 133.50W) is located on a hill above the Mackenzie River close to the
            Arctic Ocean. It is 103.2 m above mean sea level and has been operating since late 1998, with reliable data
            after about February 2000. It is operated by the Geophysical Institute of the University of Alaska, in
            cooperation with Environment Canada. Chris Strube, and previously Jeff Allen, helps to keep things running.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>68.33,-133.5,103.2</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Davis Antarctica Spectrometer</name>
        <description>type: SpectroPhotometer

            The Davis, Antarctica (68.48S, 77.97E; 25 m alt) Czerny-Turner (CZT) scanning spectrophotometer obtains
            mesosphere temperatures from ratios of the hydroxyl (OH) (6-2) band during nighttime hours. The
            spectrophotometer was in campaign operation March to October 1990 and April to August 1994, and has had
            continuous winter operations since March 1995. (See Greet et al., 1998; French et al., 2000; Burns et al.,
            2002.)

            Hydroxyl (6-2) band rotational temperatures are derived using Langhoff et al. (1986) transition
            probabilities, which are approximately 2 K higher than the temperatures derived by French et al. (2000)
            using experimentally derived P1 branch ratios with a slit width of 100 microns. The hydroxyl layer is
            centered at a mean height of 87+/-4 km with a mean thickness of 8 km. WINDII data showed that the hydroxyl
            layer often (up to 25% of the the time) has 2 peaks between 83 and 93 km (She and Lowe, 1998). The
            brightness of this layer usually decreases during the night.

            The spectrophotometer has a 6 degree field-of-view (fov) that was aligned 30-degrees above the horizon in a
            direction +130 E from Davis away from auroral precipitation in 1990 (Greet et al., 1998). An order
            separating filter was not used in 1990. Starting in 1994, the optical axis was aligned in the zenith, with a
            resultant area of about 8 km x 8 km at 87 km. In practice the field of view is defined by the diffraction
            grating. The diffraction grating rotates about the vertical axis as it scans, so that the area of the
            grating directly viewing the sky decreases with wavelength (when the grating is at vertical the fov is
            zero). Thus the fov corresponding to the grating vertical axis varies with grating rotation angle and
            consequently with wavelength. The instrument is aligned towards the SE (+130 E), but rotates about the
            vertical as the spectrum is sampled, so these observations are considered to be in the vertical.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-68.48,77.97,25.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Collm LF Radar</name>
        <description>type: LFradar

            The Collm Geophysical Observatory (51.31 N 13.003 E) uses the closely spaced receiver method at 177, 225,
            and 270 kHz. Two receivers are used to the geographic north and east of the radar so the center of the
            reflection point triangle is near (52 N, 15 E). The measurements of the nighttime neutral winds and virtual
            heights are averaged over half-hour intervals from measurements of about 3/minute for winds and about
            300/minute for virtual heights.

            The virtual height of the half-hour means is converted to true height using an empirical relation with
            linear height reduction (Kurschner et al, 1987). Then the half-hour means of the zonal and meridional winds
            are put through a multiple regression analysis to determine the altitude dependance of the prevailing and
            semi-diurnal tidal winds. To improve the spectral sensitivity, it proved useful to assume a circularly
            polarized tidal wind, which is acceptable for mid-latitudes. Therefor, the amplitude of the zonal and
            meridional semi-diurnal tidal wind is equal, and the phase of the meridional wind is 3 hours earlier than
            that of the zonal wind. Similarly, the amplitude of the zonal and meridional diurnal tidal wind is equal,
            and the phase of the meridional wind is 6 hours earlier than that of the zonal wind. However, the 24 hour
            component is normally only computed for the height of 95 km where the signal is a maximum. The result should
            be treated with some caution considering the fact that the observations are nighttime only.

            The phases are in mean local solar time (SLT). There is 1 hour between SLT and UT since the measurements are
            near 15E. Most of the calculations are for the period of a month. Extra information of interest such as
            seasonal transitions and the quasi two-day wave are in catalogue records. The data in the CEDAR Data Base
            are from January 1993 to January 1997, with selected Lower Thermosphere Coupling Study (LTCS) periods
            earlier.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>51.31,13.003</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Eureka, Canada Michelson Interferometer</name>
        <description>type: MichelsonInterferometer

            A near infrared (NIR) BOMEM MB160 Michelson interferometer (MI) has operated at Eureka (80.22 N, 86.18 W),
            Canada, at 139 m above mean sea level since October, 1992.

            The MI scans the dark sky NIR airglow emissions between ~5000-10000 cm-1. A periscope directs the airglow
            into the MI sequentially from four locations: overhead, and at an elevation angle of 25 deg at azimuth
            angles of 0 (geog N), 120, and 240 deg. The periscope dwells at each of the positions for about 8 min,
            averaging several scans. Airglow hydroxyl Meinel (OH-M) band emissions peak at 87 km and are located between
            about 83 and 89 km. For an elevation angle of 25 deg, the 87 km peak is located at a latitude spacing of
            1.61 degrees, or about 179 km away.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>80.22,-86.18,139.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Atlanta Georgia Meteor Wind Radar</name>
        <description>type: MeteorWindRadar

            Between August 1974 and April 1987, the Georgia Tech Radio Meteor Wind Facility was in routine operation,
            measuring winds between 80 and 100 km over Atlanta, Georgia, USA. A series of technical reports has been
            published on the measurements (Roper, 1978; 1982; 1984; 1987).

            At meteor heights, the viewing area was a slab 400 km in diameter across. Significant results were achieved
            by averaging from 5 days to 2 weeks of data. The local mean solar time for Atlanta is the Universal Time
            minus 5 hours and 37 minutes. The tabulations are the result of matching the data against the model
            developed by Groves (1959). The model assumes cubic variations with height H for prevailing, diurnal and
            semidiurnal components of the horizontal wind.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>34.0,-84.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>South Pole Fabry-Perot Interfer Spectr</name>
        <description>type: FabryPerot

            The Fabry-Perot Interferometric Spectrometer at Amundsen-Scott South Pole Station (90.00S) has been operated
            since 1989 by the Department of Earth and Space Sciences, University of Washington, in cooperation with the
            Geophysical Institute of the University of Alaska. The instrument is located within 150 feet of the South
            Pole at 2835 m above mean sea level. The geographic longitude is used to reckon the azimuthal direction of
            observation, with 0 E corresponding to 0 deg azimuth. The apex magnetic coordinates of South Pole at 250 km
            height in 1992 were (-74.4, 17.7), with a magnetic declination of -21.37 deg (or 158.63 E toward the compass
            south pole), an inclination of -74.78 deg, and 0 UT at 2039 MLT. The invariant (apex) South Pole at 250 km
            height was at (74.2S, 126.0E), and the perpendicular to the magnetic latitude circle pointed to 125.6E.
            Hernandez et al (1991) used magnetic south towards 120 E, with 0 UT at 2023 MLT. The magnetic grid is useful
            for ordering the red line observations at about 250 km height, but not for other observations from emissions
            below 100 km height.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-90.0,0.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Kharkov Ukraine I.S. Radar</name>
        <description>type: IncoherentScatterRadar

            The Kharkov incoherent scatter radar is located at (49.7N, 36.3E; 97 m above mean sea level) in Ukraine.
            Operations started around 1981. There are 2 antennas, a zenith antenna and a steerable antenna, but both are
            assigned the same kinst of 45, and the elevation angle will determine which is being used.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>49.7,36.3,97.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Saskatoon HF Radar</name>
        <description>type: HFRadar

            The Saskatoon HF radar is located in central Saskatchewan (52.16 deg N, -106.53 deg E) and looks over a
            section of ionosphere poleward of 53 deg N that covers north-central Canada including Hudson Bay and the
            Canadian arctic archipelago. It has operated since 1993. The facility is part of the SuperDARN network of HF
            radars that extends from western North America to Scandinavia in the Northern hemisphere and covers much of
            Antarctica in the Southern hemisphere. The SuperDARN radar for the most direct 2-D merging of Saskatoon
            velocity data is located at Kapuskasing, Canada.

            The radar forms and steers its beam by the phasing of transmissions from 16 elements in a linear antenna
            array. A second 4-element array provide the capability to measure elevation angle. The basic radar operation
            consists of the following steps: i) selection of a beam position (0-15), ii) search for the quietest 5-kHz
            channel about the assigned transmitting frequency (8-20 MHz), iii) repeated transmission of a multi-pulse
            sequence over the selected integration period and reception of backscattered signal with gating in range
            (1-70), and iv) calculation of the auto-correlation functions (ACFs). These operations are usually carried
            out in sequence for the 16 beam positions, which collectively constitute 1 scan. The beam integration period
            is typically 6 or 7 sec, and the scan repeat time is 96 sec or 120 sec. Within a scan, beam 0 corresponds to
            the most westward beam position and beam 15 to the most eastward. The azimuth sector scanned is
            approximately 50 deg wide and is centered on 23.1 deg E of N.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>52.16,-106.53</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Rarotonga Cook Islands MF RADAR</name>
        <description>type: MFRadar

            The Rarotonga, Cook Islands (21.21S, 159.77W; 2 m alt) 1.98 MHz MF radar has been in operation since 2000.
            On day 359 of 2001 at 89 km altitude, the apex magnetic coordinates were (-22.9, -84.9) degrees. The
            magnetic inclination and declination angles were -39.5 deg and 13.5 deg. The magnetic local time at 0
            Universal Time (UT) is about 1316 MLT. The solar local time (SLT) is UT minus 10 hours and 39 minutes
            (-159.77/15.=-10.651).
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-21.21,-159.77,2.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Ascension Island Meteor RADAR</name>
        <description>type: MeteorWindRadar

            The Ascension Island (7.96 S, 14.38 W; alt 170 m) 43.50 MHz meteor radar has been in operation since August
            1999. On day 359 of 2001 at 89 km altitude, the apex magnetic coordinates were (-19.6, 55.0) degrees. The
            magnetic inclination and declination angles were -39.3 deg and -16.8 deg. The magnetic local time at 0
            Universal Time (UT) is about 2235 MLT. The solar local time (SLT) is UT minus 58 minutes (14.38/15=0.959).
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-7.96,-14.38,170.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Sondre Stromfjord Digisonde</name>
        <description>type: IonSonde

            The Digisonde (DISS) located at Sondre Stromfjord, Greenland (67.0N,309.05E) and operated by the University
            of Massachusettes Lowell Center for Atmospheric Research, for Air Force Research Laboratory Hanscom AFB, has
            produced ion velocity measurements and electron density profiles since 1986. The data are originally
            collected in local magnetic coordinates, and then converted to geographic coordinates using the declination
            angle of -41.2 for an altitude of 0 km.

            The Digisonde generally operates in a 15 minute cycle mode, where the first 2-3 minutes an ionogram is
            recorded followed generally by 1-2 minutes of drift measurements, with the remaining 10-12 minutes idle.
            Sometimes the cycle time is 5 minutes. The range of altitudes is about 200-450 km, where the mean for the
            1993 data was set to 250 km.

            Digisondes transmit HF radio waves illuminating a large ionospheric area of several hundred kilomaters
            diameter over the sounder. Radio waves are sent up and reflected off orthogonal surfaces. Each reflection
            point is considered to be a separate source and has associated with it a line- of-sight (los) Doppler
            velocity measurement. Making the assumption that the main contribution to the measured Doppler shifts
            results from the uniform horizontal bulk motion of the plasma, the los velocity and source location are used
            to calculate the velocity vector by least squares fit.

            The drift mode resulted in up to a maximum of 64 sources in a single integration period of 5 seconds. One
            minute data is obtained where the error bar is the average of the standard deviations from 12 5-second
            integrations, while the value of each velocity component is the median from a further velocity distribution
            found using all the data points in the entire one minute period. The 1 minute results were taken and
            reported every 15 minutes.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>67.0,-50.95</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>USU ALO Rayleigh LIDAR</name>
        <description>type: RayleighLidar

            The Utah State University (USU) Rayleigh lidar at the Atmospheric Lidar Observatory (ALO) is run by the
            Center for Atmospheric and Space Sciences (CASS). It is located at Logan, Utah at (41.74N, 111.81W) on the
            roof of the Science and Engineering Research (SER) building on campus. The height is 1466 m using the WGS84
            geoid to represent the earth. The lidar is operated in the vertical direction and can obtain data on all
            non-heavy cloud nights. (Thin cirrus clouds are OK.) An operator is present to operate the system and for
            aircraft safety. The lidar started operations in August 1993, with relatively regular operations up to the
            present except between April 1997 and May 1998 when the lidar was not operating.

            The lidar operates at a wavelength of 532 nm up to about 500 km, but collects meaningful data only between
            about 45 and 100 km. The height resolution of the data is originally 37.5 m using 3600 shots (30 per sec)
            over 2 minutes. However, averaging is done over 81 range gates (81*37.5m = 3.0375 km) with a sliding average
            reported every 112.5 m (3 range gates). The number of 2-min integrations is reported as Code 415. Hourly
            averages of 29 or less 2 minute intervals are calculated, where cloudy or otherwise unusable periods have
            been eliminated in the hourly average (kindat=17002). Nightly average profiles are also computed.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>41.74,-111.81</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Fort Yukon Alaska 4 Channel Photometer</name>
        <description>type: MultiChannelPhotometer

            The Aerospace 4 channel filter photometer at Fort Yukon, Alaska (66.57N, 214.73E) was developed to estimate
            the energy flux of auroral electrons, their average energy Eo (usually from 0.1 to 30 keV using a modified
            Gaussian or Maxwellian shape), and a scale factor fo for the atomic oxygen densities [O] from an MSIS model
            atmosphere. The [O] densities using the scaling factor fo can be compared to GUVI/TIMED estimates. The
            technique is only valid for clear night conditions where the solar zenith angle (sza) is greater than 102
            deg (code 4102=1), and there is enough auroral emission (427.8 nm brightness, code 2421). Fort Yukon apex
            magnetic coordinates are (67.3, -94.7) at 110 km in 2001, with 0 UT corresponding to 12:36 MLT. The magnetic
            inclination and declination angles are 78.7 deg and 25.6 deg. The photometer looks up the magnetic field
            line with a field of view (fov) of about 1 deg. The data rate can be programmed, but typically each channel
            is integrated for 1 sec, where the whole cycle including filter moves takes about 8 sec.

            The 4 channels correspond to:

            1. N2+ (427.8 nm, blue) first negative group (1NG) 0,1 molecular band
            2. OI (630.0 nm, red) forbidden
            3. OI (844.6 nm, eight) permitted
            4. N2 (871.0 nm or 871.4 nm) first positive group (1PG) 2,1 molecular band
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>66.57,-145.27</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Saint Santin: Mende receiver</name>
        <description>type: IncoherentScatterRadar

            The incoherent scatter transmitter station at St. Santin, France (44.6N, 2.2E) operated between 1963 and
            1987. The CEDAR Data Base holds all the data taken from 1966 until the end. Up until June 1973 and after
            July of 1986, the only receiver station operating was located at Nancay (47.4N, 2.2E). Between 1973 and
            1986, 2 other receivers also operated at Montpazier (44.7N, 0.8E) and at Mende (44.5N, 3.45E).

            In general, the daytime height range is 105 to 350 km, while the nighttime height range is 200 to 500 km.
            Before January 1, 1969, the faraday correction is not taken into account in the computation. The spectrum
            are analysed following the scheme described in Waldteufel (1970). The ion drift component is quasi parallel
            to the magnetic field as measured by the Nancay receiving station. Because the transmitter is not located at
            the receiving location, the bisector velocity is plotted for the period when only Nancay data were received.
            When all 3 receivers were on, then the data are 30 minute averages and the ion drifts in the geomagnetic
            coordinate system are calculated.

            There are 4 areas in the summary plots. There are image plots as a function of height and time of the
            electron density, electron temperature, and ion temperature. Bin sizes are 40 minutes in time and 40 km in
            height. For the Nancay period alone there is also an image plot of the bisector velocity, while this is
            replaced by line plots of the ion drift in the perpendicular east, north and parallel directions at the
            altitude closest to 300 km. when there are 3 receivers.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>44.6,2.2</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Chatanika AK I.S. Radar</name>
        <description>type: IncoherentScatterRadar

            The incoherent scatter transmitter station at Chatanika, Alaska (65.1N, 147.4W) operated between 1971 and
            1982. It was moved to Sondrestrom in 1982-1983, where it has been in operation since 1983. There are
            generally 7 record types (KINDAT) for each Chatanika experiment that are usually inputs or outputs to a
            program called VAST, which calculates electric fields, vector velocities and conductivities. VAST assumes
            the velocity field varies linearly with time. Data from five positions are used to find the three
            line-of-sight velocities at the time of the middle observation. Full error propagation, including covariance
            terms, is included. The density and temperature data are combined to obtain a spatial average for the time
            of the middle observation.

            In addition, several criterea involving the least squares fit, as well as relative absolute uncertainties,
            have been examined to determine whether the derived F-region vector velocities are converted to electric
            fields, and the good values are height integrated to find the best possible estimate of the electric field.
            Starting in the D-region, the averaged electron densities are used to calculate the conductivities. The
            calculation has been improved to explicitly include the ion-neutral collision frequencies and to include a
            model atmosphere.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>65.1,-147.4</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>EISCAT: Sodankyla antenna</name>
        <description>type: IncoherentScatterRadar

            The EISCAT (European Incoherent SCATter) facility in Scandinavia consists of a transimitter/receiver station
            at Tromso, Norway (69.6N, 19.2E), and receiver stations at Kiruna, Sweden (67.9N, 20.4E) and Sodankyla,
            Finland (67.4N, 26.6E). The facility has been in operation since 1981, and recently expanded to include a
            facility at Svalbard, which will have its own web page when data are included in the CEDAR Data Base.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>69.9,19.2</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Syowa Antarctica HF Radar</name>
        <description>type: HFRadar

            The Syowa South HF radar is located in Antarctica (69.00 S, 39.58 E) and looks over a section of ionosphere
            poleward (southward) of 70 deg S that includes central Antarctica. It has operated since 1995. The facility
            is part of the SuperDARN network of HF radars that extends from western North America to Scandinavia in the
            Northern hemisphere and covers much of Antarctica in the Southern hemisphere. The SuperDARN radar for the
            most direct 2-D merging of Syowa velocity data is located at SANAE (South African National Antarctic
            Expedition), Antarctica.

            The radar forms and steers its beam by the phasing of transmissions from 16 elements in a linear antenna
            array. A second 4-element array provide the capability to measure elevation angle. The basic radar operation
            consists of the following steps: i) selection of a beam position (0-15) ii) search for the quietest 5-kHz
            channel about the assigned transmitting frequency (8-20 MHz) iii) repeated transmission of a multi-pulse
            sequence over the selected integration period and reception of backscattered signal with gating in range
            (1-70) iv) calculation of the auto-correlation functions (ACFs). These operations are usually carried out in
            sequence for the 16 beam positions, which collectively constitute 1 scan. The beam integration period is
            typically 6 or 7 sec, and the scan repeat time is 96 sec or 120 sec. Within a scan, beam 0 corresponds to
            the most westward beam position and beam 15 to the most eastward. The azimuth sector scanned is
            approximately 50 deg wide and is centered on 159 deg E of N, or about 52 degrees west of the general scan
            position of Syowa East.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-69.0,39.58</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Sondrestrom I.S. Radar</name>
        <description>type: IncoherentScatterRadar

            The incoherent scatter transmitter station at Kangerlussuaq (Sondrestrom), Greenland (66.99N, 50.95W, 185m
            ASL) has been in operation since February, 1983. It was moved from Chatanika, Alaska in 1982-1983, where it
            operated from July 1971 to March 1982. On day 359 of 2001 at 110 km altitude, the apex magnetic coordinates
            were (73.0, 40.5) degrees. The magnetic inclination and declination angles were 80.1 deg and -35.2 deg. The
            magnetic local time at 0000 Universal Time (UT) is about 2137 MLT. The solar local time (SLT) is UT minus 3
            hours and 24 minutes (-50.95/15.=-3.397).
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>66.9,-50.95,185.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Millstone Hill Fabry-Perot</name>
        <description>type: GroundBasedInstrument, FabryPerot

            The Millstone Hill Fabry Perot interferometer is operated by MIT in cooperation with the University of
            Pittsburgh. The interferometer is located near the Millstone Hill incoherent scatter radar at latitude 42
            degrees 37 minutes North (42.62) and longitude 71 degrees 27 minutes West (-71.45). Mean local solar time
            differs from UT by -(4 hour 46 minutes). The local magnetic field has a 15 degree variation to the West and
            an inclination of 72 degrees.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>42.62,-71.45</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Poker Flat Alaska MST Radar</name>
        <description>type: MSTRadar

            The Poker Flat MST radar was located at the Poker Flat Rocket range about 200 m above mean sea level in
            Alaska at (65.13N, 145.46W), and operated between 1979 and 1987. The last 2 years are not in the CEDAR Data
            Base. The inclination angle is about 77 degrees, and the declination is about 29 degrees to the east of
            north.

            The Poker Flat radar was a high power radar, with three narrow beams. One beam looked vertically
            (kindat=20003) and the other two were inclined at 15 degrees to vertical, or at an elevation angle of 75
            degrees. The 'east' beam had an azimuth 26 degrees north of east (kindat=20001) while the 'north' beam had
            an azimuth 26 degrees west of north (kindat=20002). Most of the data were taken using all three beams but
            some, especially in the early days, were taken with only the vertical beam or with only the oblique beams.
            During an experiment one or more beams were sometimes inactivated. The cycle time for a complete set of
            vertical and oblique records seldom exceeded 10 min and was typically 1 min. When available, velocity
            measurements from the two oblique beams were combined to give eastward and northward components of the
            neutral wind (kindat=20004). The velocity spread is twice the square root of the second moment of the power
            spectrum and is a measure of shear or turbulence in the measurement volume.

            Data quality below 5 km is definitely dubious and below 8 km should be treated with suspicion due to
            recovery problems. The more obviously false data have been removed from this data set but consistently false
            data are hard to distinguish from the real thing and may be included.

            The original Poker Flat data set has been subjected to an extensive set of checks to remove various
            interference modes, outliers and otherwise non-atmoshperic data. The parameters for the remaining data have
            been averaged for all appropriate records that commenced within a one hour interval. Note that these are
            averages of the derived parameters and not parameters derived from an average velocity spectrum.

            In the absence of any signal echo the main contribution to noise is the radio noise from our galaxy. Hence
            there is a siderial variation (of about 4 db) in the noise level. Atmospheric absorption events reduce the
            level of noise. Receiver gain and cable attenuation fluctuations may have a small influence. Operator
            modification of gain controls are rare. Strong signals can corrupt the computation through their sidelobes.
            The errors given are the root mean square values of the deviation from the mean for that hour.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>65.13,-145.46</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Rothera, Antarctica MF RADAR</name>
        <description>type: MFRadar

            The Rothera, Antarctica (67.57S, 68.12W; ~5 m alt) 1.98 MHz MF radar was in operation 1997-1998, and was
            reinstalled in 2002. The data are noisy. On day 359 of 2001 at 89 km altitude, the apex magnetic coordinates
            were (-52.6, 7.6) degrees. The magnetic inclination and declination angles were -59.9 deg and 20.5. deg. The
            magnetic local time at 0000 Universal Time (UT) is about 1925 MLT. The solar local time (SLT) is UT minus 4
            hours and 32 minutes (-68.12/15.=-4.5413).
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-67.57,-68.12,5.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Esrange, Sweden Meteor RADAR</name>
        <description>type: MeteorWindRadar

            The Esrange, Sweden (67.89N, 21.08E; alt ??? m) 32.5 MHz meteor radar has been in operation since August
            1999. On day 359 of 2001 at 89 km altitude, the apex magnetic coordinates were (64.8, 103.2) degrees. The
            magnetic inclination and declination angles were 77.2 deg and 5.8 deg. The magnetic local time at 0
            Universal Time (UT) is about 0148 MLT. The solar local time (SLT) is UT plus 1 hour and 24 minutes
            (21.08/15=1.405).
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>67.89,21.08</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>EISCAT: Kiruna antenna</name>
        <description>type: IncoherentScatterRadar

            The EISCAT (European Incoherent SCATter) facility in Scandinavia consists of a transimitter/receiver station
            at Tromso, Norway (69.6N, 19.2E), and receiver stations at Kiruna, Sweden (67.9N, 20.4E) and Sodankyla,
            Finland (67.4N, 26.6E). The facility has been in operation since 1981, and recently expanded to include a
            facility at Svalbard, which will have its own web page when data are included in the CEDAR Data Base.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>69.6,19.2</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Poker Flat AK Scanning Imaging F-P Spec</name>
        <description>type: FabryPerot

            The all-sky scanning imaging Fabry-Perot Spectrometer (ASIFPS) at Poker Flat, Alaska (65.12N, 147.43W) is
            also known as a Scanning Doppler Instrument (SDI). It is an extremely high resolution optical imaging
            spectrometer. It measures the angular distribution of Doppler shifts and of Doppler broadening of optical
            airglow and auroral light emitted from the Earth's upper atmosphere, across the entire sky scene that is
            visible to the gorund-based instrument, down to a zenith angle of ~75 deg. The distributions of Doppler
            shifts and of Doppler broadening across the sky are used to infer geographic maps of the wind and
            temperature distributions prevailing within the emission layer.

            The instrument is located on a ridge-top, 50 km ENE from Fairbanks and at 440 m above mean sea level. It has
            been operated since November 1994 by the Geophysical Institute of the University of Alaska as part of the
            optical diagnostic instruments at the Poker Flat Research Range. The building is aligned in the magnetic
            north direction at 28.5 degrees azimuth to NE. The apex magnetic coordinates of Poker Flat in December 2001
            at 240 km were (65.25, -95.41), with a magnetic declination of 23.56 deg to NE, an inclination of 77.36 deg
            to SW, and 0 UT at 1231 MLT. At 96 km, apex coordinates are (65.23, -95.45), with a magnetic declination of
            24.28 deg, an inclination of 77.37 deg, and 0 UT at 1231 MLT. The observations are reported in approximate
            local magnetic coordinates, rotated 28.5 degrees clockwise from geographic, and also in geographic
            coordinates. The magnetic skew angle (code 1020) is about 4.6 deg, which is negligible.

            The instrument is based on a 100-mm aperture capacitance-stabilized Fabry-Perot etalon, the plates of which
            are piezoelectrically scannable in spacing over approximately 1.5 orders of interference (at 630-nm) about a
            nominal 20-mm gap. Skylight is coupled into the etalon through an all-sky lens and optical relay system
            which maps an approximately 75-degree half-angle field-of-view onto 6 orders of interference at the etalon.
            Interference fringes formed by the etalon are conjugate with the sky. The sky, modulated by this fringe
            pattern, is re-imaged onto an intensified CCD detector, after first passing through a narrow-band
            interference filter.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>65.12,-147.43</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>EISCAT I.S. Radar</name>
        <description>type: IncoherentScatterRadar

            The EISCAT (European Incoherent SCATter) facility in Scandinavia consists of a transimitter/receiver station
            at Tromso, Norway (69.6N, 19.2E), and receiver stations at Kiruna, Sweden (67.9N, 20.4E) and Sodankyla,
            Finland (67.4N, 26.6E). The facility has been in operation since 1981.

            The power profiles are calibrated with an on-site ionosonde, and are then corrected for Te and Ti effects
            which are deduced from the auto-correlation functions (ACFs). The collision frequency model used is the CIRA
            1972 model atmosphere in Banks and Kockarts (1973), in Aeronmy Part A. The NO+ composition is assumed zero
            above 300 km. Perpendicular and parallel ion velocities were calculated routinely beginning in March, 1990.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>69.6,19.2</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Thule Greenland Fabry-Perot</name>
        <description>type: FabryPerot

            The Thule Fabry Perot interferometer, operated by the Space Physics Research Laboratory, Department of
            Atmospheric, Oceanic and Space Sciences of the University of Michigan is located at latitude 76.53N and
            longitude 68.44W.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>76.53,-68.44</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Tromso Norway MF Radar</name>
        <description>type: MFRadar

            The Tromso MF radar is located in Norway (70 N, 19 E). The mean solar local time (SLT) is Universal Time
            (UT) plus 1 hour and 18 minutes. (SLT = UT + 1:18). The phases are in SLT and the measurement days start at
            0 UT. The Tromso MF radar data is obtained and analyzed by the Saskatoon MF radar scientists, and has
            provided considerable mean winds (Manson et al., 1990a and 1991a) and tidal data (Manson et al, 1989).
            LTCS-1 and LTCS-2 are described for all middle atmosphere radars in Manson et al. (1990b, 1991b). MF radars
            use the spaced antenna method. Harmonic analysis is applied to hourly mean winds (weighted by data yield per
            hour) at individual heights to obtain tides for the prime LTCS or stated intervals. Typical standard
            deviations for means, 12-hour and 24-hour tides are in the above LTCS papers. Tides of the month for Tromso
            are means of 4-day fits (the amplitudes are arithmetic means). Data up to 99 km are real heights --- above,
            they are from the E-region, a layer about 5 km centered near 102 km.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>70.0,19.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Saint Santin I.S. Radar</name>
        <description>type: IncoherentScatterRadar

            The incoherent scatter transmitter station at St. Santin, France (44.6N, 2.2E) operated between 1963 and
            1987. The CEDAR Data Base holds all the data taken from 1966 until the end. Up until June 1973 and after
            July of 1986, the only receiver station operating was located at Nancay (47.4N, 2.2E). Between 1973 and
            1986, 2 other receivers also operated at Montpazier (44.7N, 0.8E) and at Mende (44.5N, 3.45E).

            In general, the daytime height range is 105 to 350 km, while the nighttime height range is 200 to 500 km.
            Before January 1, 1969, the faraday correction is not taken into account in the computation. The spectrum
            are analysed following the scheme described in Waldteufel (1970). The ion drift component is quasi parallel
            to the magnetic field as measured by the Nancay receiving station. Because the transmitter is not located at
            the receiving location, the bisector velocity is plotted for the period when only Nancay data were received.
            When all 3 receivers were on, then the data are 30 minute averages and the ion drifts in the geomagnetic
            coordinate system are calculated.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>44.6,2.2</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Platteville, Colorado MF RADAR</name>
        <description>type: MFRadar

            The Platteville 2 MHz MF radar is located in Colorado, USA (40.18N, 104.7W; 1505 m alt), and has been in
            operation since December 1999, with a data gap from March to July 2000 because of system problems. On day
            359 of 2001 at 89 km altitude, the apex magnetic coordinates were (49.3, -39.6) degrees. The magnetic
            inclination and declination angles were 67.2 deg and 10.0 deg. The magnetic local time at 0000 Universal
            Time (UT) is about 1617 MLT. The solar local time (SLT) is UT minus 6 hours and 59 minutes
            (-104.7/15=-6.98).
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>40.18,-104.7,1505.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Scott Base Antarctica MF Radar</name>
        <description>type: MFRadar

            The Scott Base MF radar (78 S, 167 E) in Antarctica is operated by the Physics Department of the University
            of Canterbury, Christchurch, New Zealand. It uses the partial-reflection, spaced antenna method (Fraser,
            1984b) and has contributed to mean wind and tidal studies (Avery et al, 1989; Fraser 1984a, 1989; Fraser et
            al 1989; Manson et al., 1989, 1990, 1991). The mean solar local time (SLT) is about 11 hours and 8 minutes
            ahead of Universal Time (UT) (i.e., 167 E / 15 deg/hr = 11.13 hours = 11 hrs 8 min). The phases are in SLT.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-78.0,167.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Mawson Antarctica MF Radar</name>
        <description>type: MFRadar

            These are tidal analyses of the mean neutral winds between 78 and 108 km over consecutive periods of 12 days
            between June 1984 and November 1990 from the MF radar located at Mawson, Antarctica (67.62 S, 62.89 E). The
            radar employs the "spaced antenna" method. The tidal analysis is a least squares fit at each altitude for
            the mean, diurnal and semi-diurnal components. The error is the standard deviation. Observations are made
            relative to mean solar time (SLT), which is about 4 hours and 12 minutes ahead of UT. (69.89 / 15 deg/hr =
            4.19 hrs = 4 hrs 12 min). The diurnal and semi-diurnal tidal components are available for this data set, and
            can be obtained from R. Vincent. They will be submitted to the CEDAR Data Base in the future. Plots of the
            mean winds are available in Vincent (1993).

            The integration time for these data is 12 days, which means that there is an overlap of days at the end of
            each year, and sometimes also just before the year's end. Echoes on the 12 days were binned into 24 1-hour
            bins of SLT. If only 15 hours or less of the full 24 hours were filled, then the tidal analysis was not
            performed. With 16-24 hours available, a least squares fit was made, where the values were weighted by the
            number of points and variance in each SLT bin. One should be wary of the results of analyses that are based
            on less than 20 hours of an SLT day.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-67.62,62.89</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Irkutsk Russia I.S. Radar</name>
        <description>type: IncoherentScatterRadar

            These experiments are a compilation of Irkutsk ISR data available in October 2002 from
            http://62.76.21.18/cgi-bin/madrigal/madInvent.cgi This is the first contribution from the Irkutsk IS radar,
            Geographic: 52.9N 103.3E 502m-msl
            Magnetic: 41.06N 104.75E
            which started full operation in 1996, although there are some single measurements from 1988.

            These data (for 1999 to 2002) have 50km spatial resolution, typically starting at 250-300 km height and with
            time resolution 20 minutes. The data are in the vertical direction.

            Higher resolution is available on request with as little as 10 km height intervals, starting at 170-200 km,
            and 2 minutes time resolution.

            The data can be used under the 'Rules of the Road' - ie, informing us at an early stage of the work and
            offering us a cooperation request at the publication stage.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>52.9,103.3,502.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Jicamarca Peru I.S. Radar</name>
        <description>type: IncoherentScatterRadar

            The 50 MHz incoherent scatter radar at Jicamarca, Peru (11.95 S, 76.87 W; 520 m alt) has been operating
            since 1963. On day 359 of 2001 at the ground, the apex magnetic lat,lon were (0.58, -5.12) deg. The magnetic
            inclination and declination angles were 1.145 deg and 0.367 deg. The magnetic local time at 0 UT is ~1835
            MLT.

            There are three basic types of operating modes for the incoherent scatter radar:

            1. Faraday rotation to obtain electron densities (Ne) and electron (Te) and ion temperatures (Ti)
            2. the drift mode
            3. the bistatic coherent radar mode (E-region Ne above Paracas)

            The drift mode, which finds perpendicular east and north (near vertical) ion drifts, has data from 1984 to
            the present. The analysis scheme to derive the drifts was changed starting in September of 1994 with a
            resulting increase in the data quality. Hard copies of time series plots of the older ion drifts are
            available upon request from NCAR.

            The bistatic coherent radar experiment involves the 50 MHz transmitter at Jicamarca and a reciever at
            Paracas (13.85 S, 76.25 W), which is about 200 km south of Jicamarca. E region (~95-110 km) electron density
            data are available using a 4 microsecond (~0.6 km) pulse length from Mar 2004. This experiment can run
            concurrently with either the Faraday rotation or the drift mode.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-11.95,-76.87,520.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Arecibo P.R. MST Radar</name>
        <description>type: MSTRadar

            The ST (strato/troposphere) radar at the National Astronomy and Ionosphere Center (NAIC) at Arecibo, Puerto
            Rico (18.3N, 66.75W), made measurements during the AIDA (Arecibo Initiative in Dynamics of the Atmosphere)
            campaign of March-May, 1989, an international multi-instrument campaign which was conducted to compare wind
            measurements in the mesosphere taken by various radar and optical devices. The tropo- and stratosphere data
            taken by the Arecibo ST radar during this period were largely decoupled from the main objectives and the
            observations of the other instruments. Data are available for both day and night times. Integration time per
            profile varies and is on the order of 30 sec to 1 min. However, because the mesosphere observations were
            interleaved with this data set, there are many gaps between profiles on the order of a few minutes. During
            AIDA, the altitude range sampled was from about 5 to 20 km, and the resolution was about 0.3 km. For this
            data set, the antenna azimuth scan pattern was very roughly as follows: 1.5 hrs at 14 or 32 deg, 10 min at
            -76 or -58 deg, 10 min at 194 or 212 deg, 30 min at 104 or 122 deg, 10 min at 194 or 212 deg, and 10 min at
            -76 or -58 deg, then repeat. Beware that the times do appear to vary. Elevation angle was fixed at about 79
            degrees. Results from AIDA have been published in J. Atmos. Terr. Phys., 55, 1993, a special issue dedicated
            to the campaign. H. Mario Ierkic was responsible for the operation of the Arecibo ST radar during AIDA, and
            John Cho put this data set into the CEDAR Data Base.

            This program extracts the following data from the Doppler spectra of the Arecibo ST radar: (1) Line-of-sight
            velocity of the clear air, (2) signal spectral width, and (3) SNR. Item (1) is self-explanatory. Items (2)
            and (3) yield information about the actual radar scattering mechanism. If the mechanism is turbulence, then
            (1) and (3) yield the turbulence intensity. For further information see Gage and Balsley [1980].
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>18.3,-66.75</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Halley Antarctica Fabry-Perot</name>
        <description>type: FabryPerot

            A Fabry Perot Interferometer is operated by the British Antarctic Survey at Halley, Antarctica. The station
            is sited on a floating ice shelf that drifts westward at around 800 m per year, requiring a new station to
            be built further to the east about every 10 years or so. The geographic coordinates are 75.5 deg S, 26.6 deg
            W, and the invariant geomagnetic coordinates are 61.5 deg S, 28.9 deg E. The magnetic inclination is 64 deg
            and magnetic north is 2 deg west of geographic north. The mean local time is 1 hour and 46 minutes
            (-26.6/15.) before Universal Time. The station was closed in 1998.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>-75.5,-26.6</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Colorado State Sodium LIDAR</name>
        <description>type: SodiumLidar

            The Colorado State University (CSU) narrow-band sodium (Na) lidar is located at Fort Collins, Colorado at
            (40.59N, 105.14W), 1570 m above sea level. It was developed with CEDAR support and has been in operation
            since 1990. The sodium layer is located between about 70 and 120 km, with a peak near 92 km. At the end of
            2001 at 92 km, the apex magnetic lat,lon coordinates were (49.61, -40.17), where the magnetic inclination
            and declination angles were 67.58 deg and 10.33 deg. The magnetic local time at 0 UT is 1612 MLT.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>40.59,-105.14,1570.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Wakkanai Japan MF radar</name>
        <description>type: MFRadar

            The Wakkanai, Japan (45.36N, 141.81E; alt ~10 m) 1.9585 MHz MF radar has been in operation since 1996. On
            day 359 of 2001 at 89 km altitude, the apex magnetic coordinates were (38.9,-146.6) degrees. The magnetic
            inclination and declination angles were 59.8 deg and -9.6 deg. The magnetic local time at 0 Universal Time
            (UT) is about 0909 MLT. The solar local time (SLT) is UT plus 9 hours and 27 minutes (141.81/15.=9.454).

            The original data files are 30 min averages of the zonal, meridional and 'vertical' velocity in UT. The UT
            time is the midpoint UT, and is also listed as the midpoint SLT. Samples are taken every 3, 4 or 5 min, so 6
            to 10 samples can be had between UT 23:45:00 and UT 00:15:00. To improve data quality, 'median screening' is
            applied inside a 1-h bin. If data points lie outside a threshold standard deviation (code 4152) of usually
            1.5 inside a 1-hr bin, they are discarded. So the low qulity (jamped) data are rejected and then the
            remaining data are averaged over 30-min bins with a threshold of usually 30% (code 4151). The number of
            points used in each direction are in codes 422, 423 and 424.

            The 'vertical' velocities (code 1432, 'contaminated neutral vertical geographic wind (+up)') are from the
            beam in the vertical direction. The antenna array in a triangle has a different beam width for different
            azimuth direction, resulting in beam widths about 20-30 deg wide. Hence, the 'vertical' velocity will be
            contaminated by horizontal wind times the sine of 10 to 15 degrees (.17 to .26). Since the horizontal winds
            are stronger than the vertical winds, even the sign could be incorrect. The standard deviations of the
            'vertical' winds are also larger than the average values.

            The MF operating frequency is 1.95550 MHz, with a peak transmitter power of 50 kW. The radar operates as a
            spaced-antenna system (Vincent, 1986), relying on coherent echo signals from middle atmosphere ionization.
            The inter-pulse period is 12.5 millisec during the day and 25 millisec during the night. There are 80
            coherent integrations during the day and 40 at night, using 240 samples in the full correlation analysis
            (FCA) of Briggs [1984] with built-in rejection criteria. [ie, if want 240 sec or 4 min integration during
            day and night, then 12.5x10-3sec * 80 integ * 240 samples = 240 sec and 25x10-3sec * 40 integ * 240 samples
            = 240 sec.]

            Data sampling is done every 2 km usually between 60-98 km for Yamagawa (60-108 km for Wakkanai, 44-108 km
            for Poker Flat). The height range of wind velocity data is variable accoding to atmospheric and radio
            conditions and is usually about 70-90 km at Yamagawa and Wakkanai during the day and 80-90 km at night
            (60-90 km/70-90 km for Poker Flat for day/night conditions).

            The pulse width is 48 microsec (27 microsec before September 1996), giving a height resolution of approx.
            7.2 km (4.1 km) assuming a simple rectangular wave pulse. For the 48-microsec case, the range of heights
            illuminated by the wave pulse = velocity of light * pulse-width / 2 = 3x10**8 m/s * 48x10-6s / 2 = 7.2 km.
            However, neutral velocities are given every 2 km.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>45.36,141.81,10.0</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Sondre Stromfjord Fabry-Perot</name>
        <description>type: FabryPerot

            The Sondre Stromfjord Fabry Perot interferometer, operated by the Space Physics Research Laboratory,
            Department of Atmospheric, Oceanic and Space Sciences of the University of Michigan is located at latitude
            66.99N and longitude 50.95W. The invariant latitude is 74 degrees, the inclination of the magnetic field is
            80 degrees and the declination of the field is -39 degrees (39 degrees to the west). Midnight local solar
            time at the site occurs at 03:24 UT, while midnight magnetic local time is 01:57 UT at the equinoxes.
            Magnetic midnight varies with season, being 15 minutes earlier at the winter solstice and 15 minutes later
            at the summer solstice compared to the equinox value.

            Currently, the interferometer observes the line profiles of the forbidden emissions OI (557.7nm) and OI
            (630.0nm). Most of the data in the CEDAR Database are 630.0nm (code 7001), with additional 557.7nm (code
            7002) data starting in 2002. The filter wheel was changed in 2002, resulting in brighter relative emissions.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>66.99,-50.95</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Goose Bay HF Radar</name>
        <description>type: HFRadar

            The Goose Bay HF radar is located in central Labrador (53.3 deg N, 299.56 deg E) and overlooks a section of
            ionosphere poleward of 55 deg N that covers northeastern Canada (Labrador, Baffin Island), the Davis Strait
            and Baffin Bay, and southern and central Greenland. It has operated since 1983. The facility is part of the
            SuperDARN network of HF radars that extends from western North America to Scandinavia in the Northern
            hemisphere and covers much of Antarctica in the Southern hemisphere. The SuperDARN radar for the most direct
            2-D merging of Goose Bay velocity data is located at Stokkseyri in western Iceland.

            The radar forms and steers its beam by the phasing of transmissions from 16 elements in a linear antenna
            array. A second array was added in 1985 to provide the capability to measure elevation angle. The basic
            radar operation consists of the following steps: i) selection of a beam position (0-15), ii) search for the
            quietest 5-kHz channel about the assigned transmitting frequency (8-20 MHz), iii) repeated transmission of a
            multi-pulse sequence over the selected integration period and reception of backscattered signal with gating
            in range (1-50), and iv) calculation of the auto-correlation functions (ACFs). These operations are usually
            carried out in sequence for the 16 beam positions, which collectively constitute 1 scan. Typical beam
            integration times are 5 and 6 sec, corresponding to scan repeat times of 80 and 96 sec, respectively. Within
            a scan, beam 0 corresponds to the most westward beam position and beam 15 to the most eastward. The azimuth
            sector scanned is eastward approximately 50 deg wide and is centered on 5 deg E of N.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>53.3,-60.44</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Stockholm Sweden IR Michelson Interfer.</name>
        <description>type: MichelsonInterferometer

            The Stockholm, Sweden (59.5N, 18.2E) IR Michelson Interferometer (IRMI) scans in the near infrared between
            wavenumbers 6000 to 10,000 cm-1 (or in the range of 1000-1667 nm in wavelength), with a 4 cm-1 resolution
            (or 0.1% resolution, about 0.3 nm). The instrument is operated by Utah State University with support from
            Stockholm University.

            The instrument measures the nightglow hydroxyl [OH]. The [OH] emission layer is centered near 87 km with a
            thickness of about 8 km. The center of the layer can vary between about 86 and 89 km, giving an error bar in
            the altitude of about +/6 km considering the thickness also. The rotational temperatures reflect the neutral
            temperatures in this altitude region. The measured parameters are the hydroxyl Meinel band rotational
            temperature in Kelvin and the hydroxyl Meinel integrated band radiance in kR and in log10(R).
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>59.5,18.2</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Qaanaaq Greenland Digisonde</name>
        <description>type: IonSonde

            The Digisonde (DGS-256) located at Qaanaaq, Greenland (77.5N, 290.6E) and operated by the University of
            Massachusettes Lowell Center for Atmospheric Research, for Phillips Laboratory Hanscom AFB, has produced ion
            velocity measurements and electron density profiles since 1983. The data are originally collected in local
            magnetic coordinates, and then converted to geographic coordinates using the declination angle of -71.0 for
            an altitude of 0 km.

            The Digisonde generally operates in a 15 minute cycle mode, where the first 2-3 minutes an ionogram is
            recorded followed generally by 1-2 minutes of drift measurements, with the remaining 10-12 minutes idle.
            Sometimes the cycle time is 5 minutes. The range of altitudes is about 200-450 km, where the mean is about
            300 km.

            Digisondes transmit HF radio waves illuminating a large ionospheric area of several hundred kilomaters
            diameter over the sounder. Radio waves are sent up and reflected off orthogonal surfaces. Each reflection
            point is considered to be a separate source and has associated with it a line- of-sight (los) Doppler
            velocity measurement. Making the assumption that the main contribution to the measured Doppler shifts
            results from the uniform horizontal bulk motion of the plasma, the los velocity and source location are used
            to calculate the velocity vector by least squares fit.

            The drift mode operated at Qaanaaq during 1989 resulted in up to a maximum of 64 sources in a single
            integration period of 5 seconds. One minute data is obtained where the error bar is the average of the
            standard deviations from 12 5-second integrations, while the value of each velocity component is the median
            from a further velocity distribution found using all the data points in the entire one minute period. The 1
            minute results were taken and reported every 15 minutes.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>77.5,-69.4</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Christmas Island ST (MEDAC) Radar</name>
        <description>type: MeteorWindRadar

            The Christmas Island ST (MEDAC) radar is located at (1.95N, 157.30W). The MEDAC (Meteor Echo Detection And
            Collection) sytem added to the ST (STratospheric) radar makes observations of winds measured from the
            backscatter off meteor trails. The system is described in Avery et al. (1990). The observations are
            described in solar local time, which is defined to be 10 hours and 32 minutes after UT (-158/15 = -10.53 or
            10 hours and 32 minutes, where the longitude used was 158 W instead of 157.30 W). These are monthly means
            corresponding to the day numbers given. The days are counted from Hawaiian Standard Time (= UT-10h). Hence,
            data starting on the first of the month actually starts at 10 UT on the first of the month, and data ending
            at the end of the month ends on the first day of the next month at 0959 UT. This data set is two years of
            data from September 1988 to August 1989, and for all of 1991. The analysis will be revised in the future.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>1.95,-157.3</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
    <Placemark>
        <name>Pykkvibaer (Iceland East) HF Radar</name>
        <description>type: HFRadar

            The Pykkvibaer HF radar is located in western Iceland (63.77 deg N, -20.54 deg E) and looks to the east over
            a section of ionosphere that includes the Greenland sea and Svaalbard. It has operated since 1995. The
            facility is part of the SuperDARN network of HF radars that extends from western North America to
            Scandinavia in the Northern hemisphere and covers much of Antarctica in the Southern hemisphere. The
            SuperDARN radar for the most direct 2-D merging of Pykkvibaer velocity data is located at Hankasalmi,
            Finland.

            The radar forms and steers its beam by the phasing of transmissions from 16 elements in a linear antenna
            array. A second 4-element array provides the capability to measure elevation angle. The basic radar
            operation consists of the following steps: i) selection of a beam position (0-15), ii) search for the
            quietest 5-kHz channel about the assigned transmitting frequency (8-20 MHz), iii) repeated transmission of a
            multi-pulse sequence over the selected integration period and reception of backscattered signal with gating
            in range (1-70), and iv) calculation of the auto-correlation functions (ACFs). These operations are usually
            carried out in sequence for the 16 beam positions, which collectively constitute 1 scan. The beam
            integration period is typically 6 or 7 sec, and the scan repeat time is 96 sec or 120 sec. Within a scan,
            beam 0 corresponds to the most westward beam position and beam 15 to the most eastward. The azimuth sector
            scanned is eastward approximately 50 deg wide and is centered on 30 deg E of N.
        </description>
        <Point>
            <coordinates>63.77,-20.54</coordinates>
        </Point>
    </Placemark>
</kml>
